Internationalized Domain Names in Applications (IDNA) makes available to DNS zone administrators a very wide range of Unicode code points. Most operators of zones should probably not permit registration of U-labels using the entire range. This is especially true of zones that accept registrations across organizational boundaries, such as top-level domains and, most importantly, the root. It is unfortunately not possible to generate algorithms to determine whether permitting a code point presents a low risk. This memo presents a set of principles that can be used to guide the decision of whether a Unicode code point may be wisely included in the repertoire of permissible code points in a U-label in a zone.

This document is not an Internet Standards Track specification; it is published for informational purposes.

This document is a product of the Internet Architecture Board (IAB) and represents information that the IAB has deemed valuable to provide for permanent record. It represents the consensus of the Internet Architecture Board (IAB). Documents approved for publication by the IAB are not a candidate for any level of Internet Standard; see Section 2 of RFC 5741.

Information about the current status of this document, any errata, and how to provide feedback on it may be obtained at http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6912.

Copyright (c) 2013 IETF Trust and the persons identified as the document authors. All rights reserved.

This document is subject to BCP 78 and the IETF Trust's Legal Provisions Relating to IETF Documents (http://trustee.ietf.org/license-info) in effect on the date of publication of this document. Please review these documents carefully, as they describe your rights and restrictions with respect to this document.

Operators of a DNS zone need to set policies around what Unicode code points are allowed in labels in that zone. Typically there are a number of important goals to consider when constructing such policies. These include, for instance, avoiding possible visual confusability between two labels, avoiding possible confusion between Fully Qualified Domain Names (FQDNs) and IP address literals, accessibility to the disabled (see "Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG) 2.0" [WCAG20] for some discussion in a web context), and other usability issues.

This document provides a set of principles that zone operators can use to construct their code point policies in order to improve usability and clarity and thereby reduce confusion.

This document uses the following terms.

      A-label: an LDH label that starts with "xn--" and meets all the
      IDNA requirements, with additional restrictions as explained in
      Section 2.3.2.1 of the IDNA Definitions document [RFC5890].

      Character: a member of a set of elements used for the
      organization, control, or representation of data.  See Section 2
      of the Internationalization Terminology document [RFC6365] for
      more details.

      Language: a way that humans communicate.  The use of language
      occurs in many forms, the most common of which are speech,
      writing, and signing.  See Section 2 of RFC 6365 for more details.

      LDH label: a string consisting of ASCII letters, digits, and the
      hyphen, with additional restrictions as explained in Section 2.3.1
      of RFC 5890.

      Public zone: in this document, a DNS zone that accepts
      registration requests from organizations outside the zone
      administrator's own organization.  (Whether the zone performs
      delegation is a separate question.  What is important is the
      diversity of the registration-requesting community.)  Note that
      under this definition, the root zone is a public zone, though one
      that has a unique function in the DNS.

      Rendering: the display of a string of text.  See Section 5 of RFC
      6365 for more details.

      Script: a set of graphic characters used for the written form of
      one or more languages.  See Section 2 of RFC 6365 for more
      details.

      U-label: a string of Unicode characters that meets all the IDNA
      requirements and includes at least one non-ASCII character, with
      additional restrictions as explained in Section 2.3.2.1 of RFC
      5890.

      Writing system: a set of rules for using one or more scripts to
      write a particular language.  See Section 2 of RFC 6365 for more
      details.

This memo does not propose a protocol standard, and the use of words such as "should" follow the ordinary English meaning, and not that laid out in [RFC2119].

In recent communications [IABCOMM1] [IABCOMM2], the IAB has emphasized the importance of conservatism in allocating labels conforming to IDNA2008 [RFC5890] [RFC5891] [RFC5892] [RFC5893] [RFC5894] [RFC5895] in DNS zones, and especially in the root zone. Traditional LDH labels in the root zone used only alphabetic characters (i.e., ASCII a-z, which under the DNS also match A-Z). Matters are more complicated with U-labels, however. The IAB communications recommended that U-labels permit only code points with a General_Category (gc) of Ll (Lowercase_Letter), Lo (Other_Letter), or Lm (Modifier_Letter), but noted that for practical considerations other code points might be permitted on a case-by-case basis.

The IAB recommendations do, however, leave some issues open that need to be addressed. It is not clear that all code points permitted under IDNA2008 that have a General_Category of Lo or Lm are appropriate for a zone such as the root zone. To take but one example, the code point U+02BC (MODIFIER LETTER APOSTROPHE) has a General_Category of Lm. In practically every rendering (and we are unaware of an exception), U+02BC is indistinguishable from U+2019 (RIGHT SINGLE QUOTATION MARK), which has a General_Category of Pf (Final_Punctuation). U+02BC will also be read by large numbers of people as being the same character as U+0027 (APOSTROPHE), which has a General_Category of Po (Other_Punctuation), and some computer systems may treat U+02BC as U+0027. U+02BC is PROTOCOL VALID (PVALID) under IDNA2008 (see the IDNA Code Points document [RFC5892]), whereas both other code points are DISALLOWED. So, to begin with, it is plain that not every code point with a

General_Category of Ll, Lo, or Lm is consistent with the type of conservatism principle discussed in Section 4.1 below or the previous IAB recommendations.

   To make matters worse, some languages are dependent on code points
   with General_Category Mc (Spacing_Mark) or General_Category Mn
   (Nonspacing_Mark).  This dependency is particularly common in Indic
   languages, though not exclusive to them.  (At the risk of vastly
   oversimplifying, the overarching issue is mostly the interaction of
   complex writing systems and the way Unicode works.)  To restrict
   users of those languages to only code points with General_Category of
   Ll, Lo, or Lm would be extremely limiting.  While DNS labels are not
   words, or sentences, or phrases (as noted in the next steps for IDN
   [RFC4690]), they are intended to support useful mnemonics.  Mnemonics
   that diverge wildly from the usual conventions are poor ones, because
   in not following the usual conventions they are not easy to remember.
   Also, wide divergence from usual conventions, if not well-justified
   (and especially in a shared namespace like the root), invites
   political controversy.

Many of the issues above turn out to be relevant to all public zones. Moreover, the overall issue of developing a policy for code point permission is common to all zones that accept A-labels or U-labels for registration. As Section 4.3 of the IDNA Protocol document [RFC5891] says, every registry at every level of the DNS is "expected to establish policies about label registrations".

For reasons of sound management, it is not desirable to decide whether to permit a given code point only when an application containing that code point is pending. That approach reduces predictability and is bound to appear subject to special pleas. It is better instead to produce the rules governing acceptance of code points in advance.

As is evident from the foregoing discussion about the Letter and Mark categories, it is simply not possible to make code point decisions algorithmically. If it were possible to develop such an algorithm, it would already exist: the DNS is hardly unique in needing to impose restrictions on code points while accommodating many different linguistic communities. Nevertheless, new guidelines can be made by starting from overarching principles. These guidelines act more as meta-rules, leading to the establishment of other rules about the inclusion and exclusion of particular code points in labels in a given zone, always based on the list of code points permitted by IDNA.

A set of principles derived from the above ideas follows in Sections 3 through 5 below. Such principles fall into three categories. Some principles apply to every DNS zone. Some additional principles apply to all public zones, including the root zone. Finally, other principles apply only to the root zone. This means that zones higher in the DNS tree tend to have more restrictive rules (since additional principles apply), and zones lower in the DNS tree tend to have less restrictive rules, since they are used within a more narrow context. In general, the relevant context for a principle is that of the zone, not that of a given subset of the user community; for the root zone, for example, the context is "the entire Internet population".

Unicode properties of a code point ought to be stable across the versions of Unicode that users of the zone are likely to have installed. Because it is possible for the properties of a code point to change between Unicode versions, a good way to predict such stability is to ensure that a code point has in fact been stable for multiple successive versions of Unicode. This principle is related to the Stability Principle in Section 4.5.

The more diverse the community using the zone, the greater the importance of following this principle. The policy for a leaf zone in the DNS might only require stability across two Unicode versions, whereas a more public zone might require stability across four or more releases before the code point's properties are considered long- lived and stable.

Every zone administrator should be sensitive to the likely use of a code point to be permitted, particularly taking into account the population likely to use the zone. Zone administrators should especially consider whether a candidate code point could present difficulty if the code point is encountered outside the usual linguistic circumstances. By the same token, the failure to support a code point that is normal in some linguistic circumstances could be very surprising for users likely to encounter the names in that circumstance.

Every zone administrator should be sensitive to ways in which a code point that is permitted could be used in support of malicious activity. This is not a completely new problem: the digit 1 and the lowercase letter l are, for instance, easily confused in many contexts. The very large repertoire of code points in Unicode (even just the subset permitted for IDNs) makes the problem somewhat worse, just because of the scale.

Public zones are, by definition, zones that are shared by different groups of people. Therefore, any decision to permit a code point in a public zone (including the root) should be as conservative as practicable. Doubts should always be resolved in favor of rejecting a code point for inclusion rather than in favor of including it, in order to minimize risk.

Just as IDNA2008 starts from the principle that the Unicode range is excluded, and then adds code points according to derived properties of the code points, so a public zone should only permit inclusion of a code point if it is known to be "safe" in terms of usability and confusability within the context of that zone. The default treatment of a code point should be that it is excluded.

The rules for determining whether a code point is to be included should be simple enough that they are readily understood by someone with a moderate background in the DNS and Unicode issues. This principle does not mean that a completely naive person needs to be able to understand the rationale for including a code point, but it does mean that if the reason for inclusion of a very peculiar code point, even a safe one, is too difficult to understand, the code point would not be permitted.

The meaning of "simple" or "readily understood" is context-dependent. For instance, the root zone has to serve everyone in the world; for practical purposes, this means that the reasons for including a code point need to be comprehensible even to people who cannot use the script where the code point is found. In a zone that permits a constrained subset of Unicode characters (for instance, only those needed to write a single alphabetic language) and that supports a

clearly delineated linguistic community (for instance, the speakers of a single language with well-understood written conventions), more complicated rules might be acceptable. Compare this principle with the Least Astonishment Principle in Section 3.2.

The rules for determining whether a code point is to be included should be predictable enough that those with the requisite understanding of DNS, IDNA, and Unicode will usually reach the same conclusion. This is not a requirement for algorithmic treatment of code points; as previously noted, that is not possible. Rather, it is to say that the consistent application of professional judgment is likely to yield the same results; combined with the principle in Section 4.1, when results are not predictable, the anomalous code point would not be permitted.

Just as in Section 4.3, this principle tends to cause more restriction the more diverse the community using the zone; it is most restrictive for the root zone. This is because what is predictable within a given language community is possibly very surprising across languages.

Once a code point is permitted, it is at least very hard to stop permitting that code point. In public zones (including the root), the list of code points to be permitted should change very slowly, if at all, and usually only in the direction of permitting an addition as time and experience indicate that inclusion of such a code point is both safe and consistent with these principles.

"Requirements for Internet Hosts - Application and Support" [RFC1123] notes that top-level labels "will be alphabetic". In the absence of widespread agreement about the force of that note, prudence suggests that U-labels in the root zone should exclude code points that are not normally used to write words, or that are in some cases normally used for purposes other than writing words. This is not the same as using Unicode's General_Category to include only letters. It is a restriction that expands the possible class of included code points beyond the Unicode letters, but only expands so far as to include the things that are normally used to create words. Under this principle, code points with (for example) General_Category Mn (Nonspacing_Mark) might be included -- but only those that are used to write words and

not (for instance) musical symbols. In addition, such marks should only be used within a label in ways that they would be used when making a word: combinations that would be nonsense when used in a word should also be rejected when tried in DNS labels. This principle should be applied as narrowly as possible; as the next steps for IDN document [RFC4690] says, "While DNS labels may conveniently be used to express words in many circumstances, the goal is not to express words (or sentences or phrases), but to permit the creation of unambiguous labels with good mnemonic value".

While many discussions of confusion have focused on characters, e.g., whether two characters are confusable with each other (and under what circumstances), a focus on characters alone could lead to the prohibition of very large numbers of labels, including many that present little risk. Instead, the focus should be on whether one label is confusable with another. For example, if a label contains several characters that are distinct to a particular script, and all of its characters are from that script, it is inherently not confusable with a label from any other script no matter what other characters might appear in it. Another label that lacks those distinguishing characters might be a problem. The notion extends from labels to domain names, in the sense that distinguishing characters used in a higher-level label may set expectations with respect to the characters in the lower-level labels. This expectation might be regarded as a benefit, but it is also a problem, since there is no technical way to require consistent policies in delegated namespaces.

The principles outlined in this document can be applied when considering any range of Unicode code points for possible inclusion in a DNS zone. It is worth observing that doing anything (especially in light of Section 4.5) implicitly disadvantages communities with a writing system not yet well understood and not represented in the technical and policy communities involved in the discussion. That disadvantage is to be guarded against as much as practical, but is effectively impossible to prevent (while still taking action) in light of imperfect human knowledge.

The principles outlined in this memo are intended to improve usability and clarity and thereby reduce confusion among different labels. While these principles may contribute to reduction of risk, they are not sufficient to provide a comprehensive internationalization policy for zone management.

Additional discussion of security considerations can be found in the Unicode Security Considerations [UTR36].

The authors thank the participants in the IAB Internationalization program for the discussion of the ideas in this memo, particularly Marc Blanchet. In addition, Stephane Bortzmeyer, Paul Hoffman, Daniel Kalchev, Panagiotis Papaspiliopoulos, and Vaggelis Segredakis made specific comments.

Bernard Aboba Jari Arkko Marc Blanchet Ross Callon Alissa Cooper Spencer Dawkins Joel Halpern Russ Housley David Kessens Danny McPherson Jon Peterson Dave Thaler Hannes Tschofenig

   [IABCOMM1] Internet Architecture Board, "IAB Statement: 'The
              interpretation of rules in the ICANN gTLD Applicant
              Guidebook'", February 2012, <http://www.iab.org/
              documents/correspondence-reports-documents/201/>.

   [IABCOMM2] Internet Architecture Board, "Response to ICANN questions
              concerning 'The interpretation of rules in the ICANN gTLD
              Applicant Guidebook'", March 2012, <http://www.iab.org/
              documents/correspondence-reports-documents/201/>.

   [RFC1123]  Braden, R., "Requirements for Internet Hosts - Application
              and Support", STD 3, RFC 1123, October 1989.

   [RFC2119]  Bradner, S., "Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate
              Requirement Levels", BCP 14, RFC 2119, March 1997.

   [RFC4690]  Klensin, J., Faltstrom, P., Karp, C., and IAB, "Review and
              Recommendations for Internationalized Domain Names
              (IDNs)", RFC 4690, September 2006.

   [RFC5890]  Klensin, J., "Internationalized Domain Names for
              Applications (IDNA): Definitions and Document Framework",
              RFC 5890, August 2010.

   [RFC5891]  Klensin, J., "Internationalized Domain Names in
              Applications (IDNA): Protocol", RFC 5891, August 2010.

   [RFC5892]  Faltstrom, P., "The Unicode Code Points and
              Internationalized Domain Names for Applications (IDNA)",
              RFC 5892, August 2010.

   [RFC5893]  Alvestrand, H. and C. Karp, "Right-to-Left Scripts for
              Internationalized Domain Names for Applications (IDNA)",
              RFC 5893, August 2010.

   [RFC5894]  Klensin, J., "Internationalized Domain Names for
              Applications (IDNA): Background, Explanation, and
              Rationale", RFC 5894, August 2010.

   [RFC5895]  Resnick, P. and P. Hoffman, "Mapping Characters for
              Internationalized Domain Names in Applications (IDNA)
              2008", RFC 5895, September 2010.

   [RFC6365]  Hoffman, P. and J. Klensin, "Terminology Used in
              Internationalization in the IETF", BCP 166, RFC 6365,
              September 2011.

   [UTR36]    Davis, M. and M. Suignard, "Unicode Security
              Considerations", Unicode Technical Report #36, July 2012.

   [WCAG20]   W3C, "Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG) 2.0",
              W3C Recommendation, December 2008,
              <http://www.w3.org/TR/2008/REC-WCAG20-20081211/>.

Authors' Addresses

   Andrew Sullivan
   Dyn, Inc.
   150 Dow St
   Manchester, NH  03101
   USA

EMail: asullivan@dyn.com

   Dave Thaler
   Microsoft
   One Microsoft Way
   Redmond, WA  98052
   USA

EMail: dthaler@microsoft.com

   John C Klensin
   1770 Massachusetts Ave, Ste 322
   Cambridge, MA  02140
   USA

Phone: +1 617 491 5735 EMail: john-ietf@jck.com

   Olaf Kolkman
   NLnet Labs
   Science Park 400
   Amsterdam  1098 XH
   The Netherlands

EMail: olaf@NLnetLabs.nl

This document specifies the process that Certification Authorities (CAs) and Relying Parties (RPs) participating in the Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI) will need to follow to transition to a new (and probably cryptographically stronger) algorithm set. The process is expected to be completed over a timescale of several years. Consequently, no emergency transition is specified. The transition procedure defined in this document supports only a top-down migration (parent migrates before children).

This memo documents an Internet Best Current Practice.

This document is a product of the Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF). It represents the consensus of the IETF community. It has received public review and has been approved for publication by the Internet Engineering Steering Group (IESG). Further information on BCPs is available in Section 2 of RFC 5741.

Information about the current status of this document, any errata, and how to provide feedback on it may be obtained at http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6916.

Copyright (c) 2013 IETF Trust and the persons identified as the document authors. All rights reserved.

This document is subject to BCP 78 and the IETF Trust's Legal Provisions Relating to IETF Documents (http://trustee.ietf.org/license-info) in effect on the date of publication of this document. Please review these documents carefully, as they describe your rights and restrictions with respect to this document. Code Components extracted from this document must include Simplified BSD License text as described in Section 4.e of the Trust Legal Provisions and are provided without warranty as described in the Simplified BSD License.

   The Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI) must accommodate
   transitions between the public keys used by Certification Authorities
   (CAs).  Transitions of this sort are usually termed "key rollover".
   Planned key rollover will occur regularly throughout the life of the
   RPKI, as each CA changes its public keys, in a non-coordinated
   fashion.  (By non-coordinated we mean that the time at which each CA
   elects to change its keys is locally determined, not coordinated
   across the RPKI.)  Moreover, because a key change might be
   necessitated by suspected private key compromise, one can never
   assume coordination of these events among all of the CAs in the RPKI.
   In an emergency key rollover, the old certificate is revoked and a
   new certificate with a new key is issued.  The mechanisms to perform
   a key rollover in RPKI (either planned or in an emergency), while
   maintaining the same algorithm suite, are covered in [RFC6489].

This document describes the mechanism to perform a key rollover in the RPKI due to the migration to a new signature algorithm suite. It specifies the process that CAs and Relying Parties (RPs) participating in the RPKI will need to follow to transition to a new (and probably cryptographically stronger) algorithm set. The process is expected to be completed over a timescale of months or years. Consequently, no emergency transition is specified. The transition procedure defined in this document supports only a top-down migration (parent migrates before children).

A signature-algorithm suite encompasses both a signature algorithm (with a specified key size range) and a one-way hash algorithm. It is anticipated that the RPKI will require the adoption of updated key sizes and/or different algorithm suites over time. This document treats the adoption of a new hash algorithm while retaining the current signature algorithm as equivalent to an algorithm migration, and requires the CA to change its key. Migration to a new algorithm suite will be required in order to maintain an acceptable level of cryptographic security and protect the integrity of certificates, Certificate Revocation Lists (CRLs), and signed objects in the RPKI. All of the data structures in the RPKI explicitly identify the signature and hash algorithms being used. However, experience has demonstrated that the ability to represent algorithm IDs is not sufficient to enable migration to new algorithm suites (algorithm agility). One also must ensure that protocols, infrastructure elements, and operational procedures also accommodate the migration from one algorithm suite to another. Algorithm migration is expected to be very infrequent, and it will require the support of a "current" and "next" suite for a prolonged interval, probably several years.

This document defines how entities in the RPKI execute a planned CA key rollover when the algorithm suite changes. The description covers actions by CAs, repository operators, and RPs. It describes the behavior required of both CAs and RPs to make such key changes work in the RPKI context, including how the RPKI repository system is used to support key rollover.

This document does not specify any algorithm suite per se. The RPKI Certificate Policy (CP) [RFC6484] mandates the use of the algorithms defined in [RFC6485] by CAs and RPs. When an algorithm transition is initiated, [RFC6485] MUST be updated (as defined in Section 4.1 of this document) to redefine the required algorithms for compliant RPKI CAs and RPs under the CP. The CP will not change as a side effect of algorithm transition, and thus the policy OID in RPKI certificates will not change.

For each algorithm transition, an additional document (the algorithm transition timetable) MUST be published (as a BCP) to define the dates for each milestone defined in this document. It will define dates for the phase transitions consistent with the descriptions provided in Section 4. It also will describe how the RPKI community will measure the readiness of CAs and RPs to transition to each phase. CAs publish certificates, CRLs, and other signed objects under the new algorithm suite as the transition progresses. This provides visibility into the deployment of the new algorithm suite, enabling the community to evaluate deployment progress. The transition procedure allows CAs to remove old certificates, CRLs, and signed products after the twilight date, which provides the ability to observe and measure the withdrawal of the old algorithm suite. Thus, the phases defined in this document enable the community to evaluate the progress of the transition. The timetable document will also describe procedures to amend the timetable if problems arise in implementing later phases of the transition. It is RECOMMENDED that the timetable document be developed by representatives of the RPKI community, e.g., IANA, Internet Registries, and network operators.

The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", "NOT RECOMMENDED" and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in [RFC2119].

This document assumes that the reader is familiar with the terms and concepts described in "Internet X.509 Public Key Infrastructure Certificate and Certificate Revocation List (CRL) Profile" [RFC5280], "X.509 Extensions for IP Addresses and AS Identifiers" [RFC3779], and "A Profile for Resource Certificate Repository Structure" [RFC6481]. Additional terms and conventions used in examples are provided below.

   Algorithm migration:  A planned transition from one signature and
               hash algorithm to a new signature and hash algorithm.

   Algorithm Suite A:  The "current" algorithm suite used for hashing
               and signing; used in examples in this document.

   Algorithm Suite B:  The "next" algorithm suite used for hashing and
               signing; used in examples in this document.

   CA X:       The CA that issued CA Y's certificate (i.e., CA Y's
               parent); used in examples in this document.

   CA Y:       The non-leaf CA; used in examples in this document.

   CA Z:       A CA that is a "child" of CA Y; used in examples in this
               document.

   Correspond: Two certificates issued under different algorithm suites
               correspond to one another if they are issued to the same
               entity by the same CA and bind identical Internet Number
               Resources (INRs) to that entity.  Two CRLs correspond if
               they are issued by the same CA and enumerate
               corresponding certificates.  Two signed objects (other
               than manifests) correspond if they are verified using
               corresponding end-entity (EE) certificates and they
               contain the same encapsulated Context Info field.  Two
               manifests correspond if they encompass corresponding
               certificates, Route Origination Authorizations (ROAs),
               CRLs, and other signed objects.  (The term "equivalent"
               is used synonymously when referring to such RPKI signed
               products.)

   Leaf CA:    A CA that issues only EE certificates.

   Non-Leaf CA:  A CA that issues certificates to other CAs.

   PoP (proof of possession):  Execution of a protocol that demonstrates
               to an issuer that a subject requesting a certificate
               possesses the private key corresponding to the public key
               in the certificate request submitted by the subject.

   ROA:        Route Origination Authorization, as defined in [RFC6482].

   Signed product set (also called set or product set):  A collection of
               certificates, signed objects, a CRL and a manifest that
               are associated by virtue of being verifiable under the
               same parent CA certificate

The "current" RPKI algorithm suite (Suite A) is defined in the RPKI CP document, by reference to [RFC6485]. When a migration of the RPKI algorithm suite is needed, the first step MUST be an update of [RFC6485] to define the new algorithm suite. The algorithm transition timeline document MUST also be published (as a BCP) to inform the community of the dates selected for milestones in the transition process, as described in Section 4.1.

   CA Ready Algorithm B Date:  After this date, all non-leaf CAs MUST be
               ready to process a request from a child CA to issue a
               certificate under the Algorithm Suite B.  All CAs
               publishing an [RFC6490] Trust Anchor Locator (TAL) for
               Algorithm Suite A MUST also publish the correspondent TAL
               for Algorithm Suite B.

   CA Go Algorithm B Date:  After this date, all CAs MUST have reissued
               all their signed product sets under Algorithm Suite B.

   RP Ready Algorithm B Date:  After this date, all RPs MUST be prepared
               to process signed material issued under Algorithm Suite
               B.

   Twilight Date:  After this date, a CA MAY cease issuing signed
               products under Algorithm Suite A.  Also, after this date,
               an RP MAY cease to validate signed materials issued under
               Algorithm Suite A.

   End-Of-Life (EOL) Date:  After this date, Algorithm Suite A MUST be
               deprecated using the process in Section 10, and all
               Algorithm Suite A TALs MUST be removed from their
               publication points.

The migration process described in this document involves a series of steps that MUST be executed in chronological order by CAs and RPs. The only milestone at which both CAs and RPs take action at the same time is the EOL Date. Due to the decentralized nature of the RPKI infrastructure, it is expected that an algorithm transition will span several years.

   In order to facilitate the transition, CAs will start issuing
   certificates using Algorithm B in a hierarchical, top-down fashion.
   In our example, CA Y will issue certificates using Algorithm Suite B
   only after CA X has started to do so (CA Y Ready Algorithm B Date >
   CA X Ready Algorithm B Date).  This ordered transition avoids the
   issuance of "mixed" suite CA certificates, e.g., a CA certificate
   signed using Suite A that contains a key from Suite B.  In the RPKI,
   a CA MUST NOT sign a CA certificate carrying a subject key that
   corresponds to an algorithm suite that differs from the one used to
   sign the certificate.  (X.509 accommodates such mixed algorithm
   certificates, but this process avoids using that capability.)  A non-
   top-down transition approach would require the use of such mixed-mode
   certificates and would lead to exponential growth of the RPKI
   repository.  Also, because the RPKI CP mandates PoP for certificate
   requests, it is not possible for a CA to request a certificate for
   Algorithm Suite B until its parent CA supports that suite.  (See
   Section 5 for more details.)

The algorithm agility model described here does not prohibit a CA from issuing an EE certificate with a subject public key from a different algorithm suite, if that certificate is not used to verify repository objects. This exception to the mixed algorithm suite certificate rule is allowed because an EE certificate that is not used to verify repository objects does not interfere with the ability of RPs to download and verify repository content. As noted above, every CA in the RPKI is required to perform a PoP check for the subject public key when issuing a certificate. In general, a subject cannot assume that a CA is capable of supporting a different algorithm. However, if the subject is closely affiliated with the CA, it is reasonable to assume that there are ways for the subject to know whether the CA can support a request to issue an EE certificate containing a specific, different public key algorithm. This document does not specify how a subject can determine whether a CA is capable of issuing a mixed suite EE certificate, because it anticipates that such certificates will be issued only in contexts where the subject and CA are sufficiently closely affiliated (for example, an ISP issuing certificates to devices that it manages).

The following figure gives an overview of the process:

Process for RPKI CAs:

     Phase 0    Phase 1   Phase 2             Phase 4  Phase 0
   --x--------x---------x-------------------x--------x---------
     ^        ^         ^                   ^        ^
     |        |         |                   |        |
    (1)      (2)       (3)                 (5)      (6)

Process for RPKI RPs:

               Phase 0              Phase 3   Phase 4  Phase 0
   -------------------------------x---------x--------x---------
     ^                            ^         ^        ^
     |                            |         |        |
    (1)                          (4)       (5)      (6)

   (1) RPKI algorithm document is updated, and the algorithm
       transition timeline document is issued
   (2) CA Ready Algorithm B Date
   (3) CA Go Algorithm B Date
   (4) RP Ready Algorithm B Date
   (5) Twilight Date
   (6) End-Of-Life (EOL) Date

Each of these milestones is discussed in the next section when each phase of the transition process is described.

Two situations have been identified that motivate pausing or rolling back the transition process. The first situation arises if the RPKI community is not ready to make the transition. For example, many CAs might not be prepared to issue signed products under Suite B, or many RPs might not be ready to process Suite B products. Under these circumstances, the timetable MUST be reissued, postponing the date for the phase in question and pushing back the dates for later phases. The other situation arises if, during the transition, serious concerns arise about the security of the Suite B algorithms. Such concerns would motivate terminating the transition and rolling back signed products, i.e., reverting to Suite A. In this case, the timetable MUST be republished, and the RPKI algorithm document MUST be superseded. The phase descriptions below allude to these two situations, as appropriate.

Phase 0 is the steady-state phase of the process; throughout this phase, Algorithm Suite A is the only supported algorithm suite in the RPKI. Phase 0 is also the steady state for the RPKI.

During Phase 0, CAs X, Y, and Z are required to generate signed product sets using only Algorithm Suite A. Also, RPs are required to validate signed product sets issued using only Algorithm Suite A.

The following figure shows an example of the structure of signed objects in the repository, indicating the algorithm suites in use and showing the relationships between three CAs (X, Y, and Z) that form a certification chain. Vertical alignment in the figure indicates objects signed by the same CA using the same private key. The differences in horizontal indentation also represent the use of different publication points for objects signed by different CAs. The characters "|->" are used for visualization purposes for both the signing relationship and the publication point change. For example, the objects CA-Y-Certificate-Algorithm-Suite-A, CA-X-CRL-Algorithm- Suite-A, and CA-X-Signed-Objects-Algorithm-Suite-A are all signed using the private key corresponding to CA-X-Certificate-Algorithm- Suite-A and published at CA X's corresponding publication point.

   CA-X-Certificate-Algorithm-Suite-A (Cert-XA)
           |-> CA-Y-Certificate-Algorithm-Suite-A (Cert-YA)
                   |-> CA-Z-Certificate-Algorithm-Suite-A (Cert-ZA)
                           |-> CA-Z-CRL-Algorithm-Suite-A (CRL-ZA)
                           |-> CA-Z-Signed-Objects-Algorithm-Suite-A
                   |-> CA-Y-CRL-Algorithm-Suite-A (CRL-YA)
                   |-> CA-Y-Signed-Objects-Algorithm-Suite-A
           |-> CA-X-CRL-Algorithm-Suite-A (CRL-XA)
           |-> CA-X-Signed-Objects-Algorithm-Suite-A

Note: Cert-XA represents the certificate for CA X, which is signed using Algorithm Suite A.

The first milestone initiates the migration process. It updates [RFC6485] with the following definitions for the RPKI:

Algorithm Suite A
Algorithm Suite B

Additionally, the new algorithm transition timeline document MUST be published with the following information:

CA Ready Algorithm B Date
CA Go Algorithm B Date
RP Ready Algorithm B Date
Twilight Date
EOL Date
Readiness metrics for CAs and RPs in each phase

Each date specified here is assumed to be at one minute after midnight, UTC. No finer granularity time specification is required or supported.

Phase 1 starts at the CA Ready Algorithm B Date. During Phase 1, all non-leaf CAs MUST be ready to process a request from a child CA to issue or revoke a certificate using Algorithm Suite B. If it is determined that a substantial number of CAs are not ready, the algorithm transition timeline document MUST be reissued, as noted in Section 4.2. However, CAs that are capable of issuing Suite B certificates may continue to do so, if requested by their child CAs. As this phase does not require any RPs to process signed objects under Suite B, and since Suite B product sets SHOULD be stored at independent publication points, there is no adverse impact on RPs. If the Suite B algorithm is deemed unsuitable, the algorithm transition timeline and the algorithm specification documents MUST be replaced, and Algorithm Suite B MUST be deprecated using the process described in Section 10.

Because the transition will happen using a hierarchical, top-down model, a child CA will be able to issue certificates using Algorithm Suite B only after its parent CA has issued its own. The RPKI provisioning protocol can identify if a parent CA is capable of issuing certificates using Algorithm Suite B and can identify the corresponding algorithm suite in each Certificate Signing Request (CSR; see Section 5). During much of this phase, the Suite B product tree will be incomplete, i.e., not all CAs will have issued products under Suite B. Thus, for production purposes, RPs MUST fetch and validate only Suite A products. Suite B products should be fetched and processed only for testing purposes.

The following figure shows the status of repository entries for the three example CAs during this phase. Two distinct certificate chains are maintained, and CA Z has not yet requested any material using Algorithm Suite B.

   CA-X-Certificate-Algorithm-Suite-A (Cert-XA)
           |-> CA-Y-Certificate-Algorithm-Suite-A (Cert-YA)
                   |-> CA-Z-Certificate-Algorithm-Suite-A (Cert-ZA)
                           |-> CA-Z-CRL-Algorithm-Suite-A (CRL-ZA)
                           |-> CA-Z-Signed-Objects-Algorithm-Suite-A
                   |-> CA-Y-CRL-Algorithm-Suite-A (CRL-YA)
                   |-> CA-Y-Signed-Objects-Algorithm-Suite-A
           |-> CA-X-CRL-Algorithm-Suite-A (CRL-XA)
           |-> CA-X-Signed-Objects-Algorithm-Suite-A

   CA-X-Certificate-Algorithm-Suite-B (Cert-XB)
           |-> CA-Y-Certificate-Algorithm-Suite-B (Cert-YB)
                   |-> CA-Y-CRL-Algorithm-Suite-B (CRL-YB)
                   |-> CA-Y-Signed-Objects-Algorithm-Suite-B
           |-> CA-X-CRL-Algorithm-Suite-B (CRL-XB)
           |-> CA-X-Signed-Objects-Algorithm-Suite-B

Phase 2 starts at the CA Go Algorithm B Date. At the start of this phase, each signed product set MUST be available using both Algorithm Suite A and Algorithm Suite B. Thus, prior to the start of this phase, every CA MUST ensure that there is a Suite B product corresponding to each Suite A product that the CA has issued. Throughout this phase, each CA MUST maintain this correspondence. During this phase, RPs MUST be prepared to validate sets issued using Algorithm Suite A and MAY be prepared to validate sets issued using the Algorithm Suite B.

   If it is determined that a substantial number of CAs are not ready,
   the algorithm transition timeline document MUST be reissued, as noted
   in Section 4.2.  (Since the processing requirement for RPs here is a
   MAY, if RPs have problems with Suite B products, this does not
   require pushing back the Phase 2 milestone, but it does motivate
   delaying the start of Phase 3.)  CAs that are capable of publishing
   products under Suite B MAY continue to do so.  Phase 2, like Phase 1,
   does not require any RPs to process signed objects under Suite B.
    Also, Suite B products SHOULD be stored at independent publication
   points so that there is no adverse impact on RPs that are not
   prepared to process Suite B products.  (See Section 9 for additional
   details.)  If the Suite B algorithm is deemed unsuitable, the

algorithm transition timeline and the algorithm specification documents MUST be replaced, and Algorithm Suite B MUST be deprecated using the process described in Section 10.

It is RECOMMENDED that RPs that can process Algorithm Suite B fetch and validate Suite B products. RPs that are not ready to process Suite B products MUST continue to make use of Suite A products. An RP that elects to validate signed product sets using both Algorithm Suite A and Algorithm Suite B should expect the same results. If there are discrepancies when evaluating corresponding signed product sets, successful validation of either product set is acceptable. A detailed analysis of the validation of multiple instances of signed objects is included in Section 6.

The following figure shows the status of the repository entries for the three example CAs throughout this phase, where all signed objects are available using both algorithm suites.

   CA-X-Certificate-Algorithm-Suite-A (Cert-XA)
           |-> CA-Y-Certificate-Algorithm-Suite-A (Cert-YA)
                   |-> CA-Z-Certificate-Algorithm-Suite-A (Cert-ZA)
                           |-> CA-Z-CRL-Algorithm-Suite-A (CRL-ZA)
                           |-> CA-Z-Signed-Objects-Algorithm-Suite-A
                   |-> CA-Y-CRL-Algorithm-Suite-A (CRL-YA)
                   |-> CA-Y-Signed-Objects-Algorithm-Suite-A
           |-> CA-X-CRL-Algorithm-Suite-A (CRL-XA)
           |-> CA-X-Signed-Objects-Algorithm-Suite-A

   CA-X-Certificate-Algorithm-Suite-B (Cert-XB)
           |-> CA-Y-Certificate-Algorithm-Suite-B (Cert-YB)
                   |-> CA-Z-Certificate-Algorithm-Suite-B (Cert-ZB)
                           |-> CA-Z-CRL-Algorithm-Suite-B (CRL-ZB)
                           |-> CA-Z-Signed-Objects-Algorithm-Suite-B
                   |-> CA-Y-CRL-Algorithm-Suite-B (CRL-YB)
                   |-> CA-Y-Signed-Objects-Algorithm-Suite-B
           |-> CA-X-CRL-Algorithm-Suite-B (CRL-XB)
           |-> CA-X-Signed-Objects-Algorithm-Suite-B

   Phase 3 starts at the RP Ready Algorithm B Date.  During this phase,
   all signed product sets are available using both algorithm suites,
   and all RPs MUST be able to validate them.  (The correspondence
   between Suite A and Suite B products was required for Phase 2 and was
   maintained throughout that phase.  The same requirements apply
   throughout this phase.)  It is RECOMMENDED that, in preparation for
   Phase 4, RPs retrieve and process Suite B product sets first and

treat them as the preferred product sets for validation throughout this phase. Thus, an RP SHOULD try to validate the sets of signed products retrieved from the Algorithm Suite B repository first.

If a substantial number of RPs are unable to process product sets signed with Suite B, the algorithm transition timeline document MUST be reissued, pushing back the date for this and later milestones, as discussed in Section 4.2. Since the Suite B products SHOULD be published at distinct publication points, RPs that cannot process Suite B products can be expected to revert to the Suite A products that still exist. If the Suite B algorithm is deemed unsuitable, the algorithm transition timeline and the algorithm specification documents MUST be replaced and Algorithm Suite B MUST be deprecated using the process described in Section 10.

There are no changes to the CA behavior throughout this phase.

Phase 4 starts at the Twilight Date. At that date, Algorithm A is labeled as "old" and the Algorithm B is labeled as "current".

During this phase, all signed product sets MUST be issued using Algorithm Suite B and MAY be issued using Algorithm Suite A. All signed products sets issued using Suite B MUST be published at their corresponding publication points. Signed products sets issued using Suite A might not be available at their corresponding publication points. Every RP MUST validate signed product sets using Suite B. RPs MAY validate signed product sets using Suite A. However, RPs SHOULD NOT assume that the collection of Suite A product sets is complete. Thus, RPs SHOULD make use of only Suite B products sets. (See Section 6 for further details.)

If it is determined that many RPs are not capable of processing the new algorithm suite, the algorithm transition timeline document MUST be reissued, pushing back the date for this and the next milestone. The document MUST require the CA not to remove Suite A product sets if this phase is delayed. If Algorithm Suite B is deemed unsuitable, the algorithm transition timeline and the algorithm specification documents MUST be replaced, Algorithm Suite B MUST be deprecated using the process described in Section 10, and CAs MUST NOT remove Suite A product sets. At this stage, RPs are still capable of processing Suite A signed products, so the RPKI is still viable.

The following figure describes a possible status for the repositories of the example CAs.

   CA-X-Certificate-Algorithm-Suite-A (Cert-XA)
           |-> CA-Y-Certificate-Algorithm-Suite-A (Cert-YA)
                   |-> CA-Y-CRL-Algorithm-Suite-A (CRL-YA)
                   |-> CA-Y-Signed-Objects-Algorithm-Suite-A
           |-> CA-X-CRL-Algorithm-Suite-A (CRL-XA)
           |-> CA-X-Signed-Objects-Algorithm-Suite-A

   CA-X-Certificate-Algorithm-Suite-B (Cert-XB)
           |-> CA-Y-Certificate-Algorithm-Suite-B (Cert-YB)
                   |-> CA-Z-Certificate-Algorithm-Suite-B (Cert-ZB)
                           |-> CA-Z-CRL-Algorithm-Suite-A (CRL-ZB)
                           |-> CA-Z-Signed-Objects-Algorithm-Suite-B
                   |-> CA-Y-CRL-Algorithm-Suite-A (CRL-YB)
                   |-> CA-Y-Signed-Objects-Algorithm-Suite-B
           |-> CA-X-CRL-Algorithm-Suite-A (CRL-XB)
           |-> CA-X-Signed-Objects-Algorithm-Suite-B

The EOL Date triggers the return to Phase 0 (steady state). At this point, the old algorithm suite, Algorithm Suite A, MUST be deprecated using the process described in Section 10.

This phase closes the loop, as the new algorithm suite (Algorithm Suite B) is now the only required algorithm suite in RPKI. From this point forward, this suite is referred to as Algorithm Suite A.

If it is determined that many RPs are not capable of processing the new algorithm suite, the algorithm transition timeline document MUST be reissued, pushing back the date for this milestone.

The migration described in this document is a top-down process where two synchronization issues need to be solved between child and parent CAs:

A child CA needs to identify which algorithm suites are supported by its parent CA.
A child CA needs to signal which algorithm suite should be used by its parent CA to sign a CSR.

The RPKI provisioning protocol [RFC6492] supports multiple algorithms suites by implementing different resource classes for each suite. Several different resource classes also may use the same algorithm suite for different resource sets.

A child CA that wants to identify which algorithm suites are supported by its parent CA MUST perform the following tasks:

1. Establish a provisioning protocol session with its parent CA.

   2.  Perform a "list" command as described in Section 3.3.1 of
       [RFC6492].

   3.  From the Payload in the "list response" resource class, extract
       the "issuer's certificate" for each class.  The algorithm suite
       for each class will match the algorithm suite used to issue the
       corresponding "issuer's certificate" (as specified in the
       SubjectPublicKeyInfo field of that certificate).

A child CA that wants to specify an algorithm suite to its parent CA (e.g., in a certificate request) MUST perform the following tasks:

   1.  Perform the tasks described above to identify the algorithm
       suites supported by its parent CA and the resource class
       corresponding to each suite.

   2.  Identify the corresponding resource class in the appropriate
       provisioning protocol command (e.g., "issue" or "revoke").

Upon receipt of a certificate request from a child CA, a parent CA will verify the PoP of the private key. If a child CA requests the issuing of a certificate using an algorithm suite that does not match a resource class, the PoP validation will fail and the request will not be performed.

During Phases 1, 2, 3, and 4, two algorithm suites will be valid simultaneously in RPKI. In this section, we describe the RP behavior when validating corresponding signed products using different algorithm suites.

During Phase 1, two corresponding instances MAY be available for each signed product, one signed under Algorithm Suite A and one under Algorithm Suite B. As noted in Section 4.4, in this phase there is a preference for Suite A product sets. All products are available under Suite A, while only some products may be available under Suite B. For production purposes, an RP MAY fetch and validate only Suite A products. Suite B products SHOULD be fetched and validated only for test purposes. When product sets exist under both suites, they should yield equivalent results, to facilitate testing. (It is not possible to directly compare Suite A and Suite B product sets, because certificates, CRLs, and manifests will appear syntactically

different. However, the output of the process, i.e., the ROA payloads -- Autonomous System number and address prefix data -- SHOULD match, modulo timing issues.)

During Phases 2 and 3 of this process, two corresponding instances of all signed products MUST be available to RPs. As noted in Section 4.5, it is RECOMMENDED that Suite B capable RPs fetch and validate Suite B products sets during Phase 2. If an RP encounters validation problems with the Suite B products, it SHOULD revert to using Suite A products. RPs that are Suite B capable MAY fetch both product sets and compare the results (e.g., ROA outputs) for testing.

In Phase 3, all RPs MUST be Suite B capable and MUST fetch Suite B product sets. If an RP encounters problems with Suite B product sets, it can revert to Suite A products. RPs encountering such problems SHOULD contact the relevant repository maintainers (e.g., using the mechanism defined in [RFC6493] to report problems.)

During Phase 4, only Suite B product sets are required to be present for all RPKI entities, as per Section 4.7. Thus, RPs SHOULD retrieve and validate only these product sets. Retrieval of Suite A products sets may yield an incomplete set of signed products and is NOT RECOMMENDED.

The algorithm migration process mandates the maintenance of two parallel but equivalent certification hierarchies during Phases 2 and 3 of the process. During these phases, a CA MUST revoke and request revocation of certificates consistently under both algorithm suites. When not performing a key rollover operation (as described in Section 8), a CA requesting the revocation of its certificate during these two phases MUST perform that request for both algorithm suites (A and B). A non-leaf CA SHOULD NOT verify that its child CAs comply with this requirement. Note that a CA MUST request revocation of its certificate relative to a specific algorithm suite using the mechanism described in Section 5

During Phase 1, a CA that revokes a certificate under Suite A SHOULD revoke the corresponding certificate under Suite B if that certificate exists. During Phase 4, a CA that revokes a certificate under Suite B SHOULD revoke the corresponding certificate under Suite A if that certificate exists.

During Phase 1, a CA may revoke certificates under Suite B without revoking them under Suite A, since the Suite B products are for test purposes. During Phase 4, a CA may revoke certificates issued under Suite A without revoking them under Suite B, since Suite A products are being deprecated.

Key rollover (without algorithm changes) is effected independently for each algorithm suite and MUST follow the process described in [RFC6489].

The two parallel hierarchies that will exist during the transition process SHOULD have independent publications points. The repository structures for each algorithm suite are described in [RFC6481].

To deprecate an algorithm suite, the following process MUST be executed by every CA in the RPKI:

   1.  Each CA MUST cease issuing certificates under the suite.  This
       means that any request for a CA certificate from a child will be
       rejected, e.g., sending an "error_response" message with error
       code "request - no such resource class", as defined in [RFC6492].

   2.  Each CA MUST cease generating signed products, except the CRL and
       manifest, under the deprecated algorithm suite.

   3.  Each CA MUST revoke the EE certificates for all signed products
       that it has issued under the deprecated algorithm suite.  The CA
       SHOULD delete these products from its publication point to avoid
       burdening RPs with the need to download and process these
       products.

   4.  Each CA MUST revoke all CA certificates that it has issued under
       the deprecated algorithm suite.

   5.  Each CA SHOULD remove all CA certificates that it has issued
       under the deprecated algorithm suite.

   6.  Each CA that publishes a TAL under the deprecated algorithm suite
       MUST removed it from the TAL's publication point.

   7.  Each CA SHOULD continue to maintain the publication point for the
       deprecated algorithm suite at least until the CRL nextUpdate.
       This publication point MUST contain only the CRL and a manifest
       for that publication point.  This behavior provides a window in
       which RPs may be able to become aware of the revoked status of
       the signed products that have been deleted.

   8.  Each RP MUST remove any TALs that is has published under the
       deprecated algorithm suite.

CAs in the RPKI hierarchy may become aware of the deprecation of the algorithm suite at different times and may execute the procedure above asynchronously relative to one another. Thus, for example, a CA may request revocation of its CA certificate, only to learn that the certificate has already been revoked by the issuing CA. The revocation of a CA certificate makes the CRL and manifest issued under it incapable of validation. The asynchronous execution of this procedure likely will result in transient "inconsistencies" among the publication points associated with the deprecated algorithm suite. However, these inconsistencies should yield "fail-safe" results, i.e., the objects signed under the deprecated suite should be rejected by RPs.

An algorithm transition in RPKI should be a very infrequent event, and it requires wide community consensus. The events that may lead to an algorithm transition may be related to a weakness of the cryptographic strength of the algorithm suite in use by RPKI, which is normal to happen over time. The procedures described in this document mean that it will take years to complete an algorithm transition. During that time, the RPKI system will be vulnerable to any cryptographic weakness that may have triggered this procedure (e.g., a downgrade attack).

This document does not describe an emergency mechanism for algorithm migration. Due to the distributed nature of RPKI and the very large number of CAs and RPs, the authors do not believe it is feasible to effect an emergency algorithm migration procedure.

If a CA does not complete its migration to the new algorithm suite as described in this document (after the EOL of the "old" algorithm suite), its signed product set will no longer be valid. Consequently, the RPKI may, at the end of Phase 4, have a smaller number of valid signed products than before starting the process. Conversely, an RP that does not follow this process will lose the ability to validate signed products issued under the new algorithm

suite. The resulting incomplete view of routing information from the RPKI (as a result of a failure by CAs or RPs to complete the transition) could degrade routing in the public Internet.

The authors would like to acknowledge the work of the SIDR working group co-chairs (Sandra Murphy, Chris Morrow, and Alexey Melnikov) as well as the contributions given by Geoff Huston, Arturo Servin, Brian Weis, Terry Manderson, Brian Dickson, David Black, and Danny McPherson.

   [RFC2119]  Bradner, S., "Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate
              Requirement Levels", BCP 14, RFC 2119, March 1997.

   [RFC3779]  Lynn, C., Kent, S., and K. Seo, "X.509 Extensions for IP
              Addresses and AS Identifiers", RFC 3779, June 2004.

   [RFC5280]  Cooper, D., Santesson, S., Farrell, S., Boeyen, S.,
              Housley, R., and W. Polk, "Internet X.509 Public Key
              Infrastructure Certificate and Certificate Revocation List
              (CRL) Profile", RFC 5280, May 2008.

   [RFC6481]  Huston, G., Loomans, R., and G. Michaelson, "A Profile for
              Resource Certificate Repository Structure", RFC 6481,
              February 2012.

   [RFC6482]  Lepinski, M., Kent, S., and D. Kong, "A Profile for Route
              Origin Authorizations (ROAs)", RFC 6482, February 2012.

   [RFC6484]  Kent, S., Kong, D., Seo, K., and R. Watro, "Certificate
              Policy (CP) for the Resource Public Key Infrastructure
              (RPKI)", BCP 173, RFC 6484, February 2012.

   [RFC6485]  Huston, G., "The Profile for Algorithms and Key Sizes for
              Use in the Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI)",
              RFC 6485, February 2012.

   [RFC6489]  Huston, G., Michaelson, G., and S. Kent, "Certification
              Authority (CA) Key Rollover in the Resource Public Key
              Infrastructure (RPKI)", BCP 174, RFC 6489, February 2012.

   [RFC6490]  Huston, G., Weiler, S., Michaelson, G., and S. Kent,
              "Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI) Trust Anchor
              Locator", RFC 6490, February 2012.

   [RFC6492]  Huston, G., Loomans, R., Ellacott, B., and R. Austein, "A
              Protocol for Provisioning Resource Certificates",
              RFC 6492, February 2012.

   [RFC6493]  Bush, R., "The Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI)
              Ghostbusters Record", RFC 6493, February 2012.

Authors' Addresses

   Roque Gagliano
   Cisco Systems
   Avenue des Uttins 5
   Rolle  1180
   Switzerland

EMail: rogaglia@cisco.com

   Stephen Kent
   BBN Technologies
   10 Moulton St.
   Cambridge, MA  02138
   USA

EMail: kent@bbn.com

   Sean Turner
   IECA, Inc.
   3057 Nutley Street, Suite 106
   Fairfax, VA  22031
   USA

EMail: turners@ieca.com

RFC 2119 defines a standard set of key words for describing requirements of a specification. Many IETF documents have found that these words cannot accurately capture the nuanced requirements of their specification. This document defines additional key words that can be used to address alternative requirements scenarios. Authors who follow these guidelines should incorporate this phrase near the beginning of their document:

The key words "MUST (BUT WE KNOW YOU WON'T)", "SHOULD CONSIDER", "REALLY SHOULD NOT", "OUGHT TO", "WOULD PROBABLY", "MAY WISH TO", "COULD", "POSSIBLE", and "MIGHT" in this document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 6919.

This document is not an Internet Standards Track specification; it is published for examination, experimental implementation, and evaluation.

This document defines an Experimental Protocol for the Internet community. This is a contribution to the RFC Series, independently of any other RFC stream. The RFC Editor has chosen to publish this document at its discretion and makes no statement about its value for implementation or deployment. Documents approved for publication by the RFC Editor are not a candidate for any level of Internet Standard; see Section 2 of RFC 5741.

Information about the current status of this document, any errata, and how to provide feedback on it may be obtained at http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6919.

Copyright (c) 2013 IETF Trust and the persons identified as the document authors. All rights reserved.

This document is subject to BCP 78 and the IETF Trust's Legal Provisions Relating to IETF Documents (http://trustee.ietf.org/license-info) in effect on the date of publication of this document. Please review these documents carefully, as they describe your rights and restrictions with respect to this document.

The phrase "MUST (BUT WE KNOW YOU WON'T)" is used to indicate requirements that are needed to meet formal review criteria (e.g., mandatory-to-implement security mechanisms), when these mechanisms are too inconvenient for implementers to actually implement.

This phrase is frequently used in a contracted form in which the parenthetical is omitted. The parenthetical may also be moved later in the sentence for stylistic reasons. If the parenthetical is present, authors MUST provide a reason why they know implementors will not heed this instruction in the parenthetical, as in the example (BUT WE KNOW YOU WON'T). In the below example, we show a case from RFC 6120 where the original text omitted the parenthetical, and we have indicated an appropriate parenthetical.

   For example: "For authentication only, servers and clients MUST
   support the SASL Salted Challenge Response Authentication Mechanism
   [SCRAM] -- in particular, the SCRAM-SHA-1 and SCRAM-SHA-1-PLUS
   variants [(BUT WE KNOW YOU WON'T, because your TLS library doesn't
   support extracting channel binding information)]."  [RFC6120]

The phrase "SHOULD CONSIDER" indicates that the authors of the specification think that implementations should do something, but they're not sure quite what.

For example: "Applications that take advantage of typed links should consider the attack vectors opened by automatically following, trusting, or otherwise using links gathered from HTTP headers." [RFC5988]

The phrase "REALLY SHOULD NOT" is used to indicate dangerous behaviors that some important vendor still does and therefore we were unable to make MUST NOT.

For example: "This command really should not be used" [RFC0493]

The phrase "OUGHT TO" conveys an optimistic assertion of an implementation behavior that is clearly morally right, and thus does not require substantiation.

   For example: "If a decision might affect semantic transparency, the
   implementor ought to err on the side of maintaining transparency
   unless a careful and complete analysis shows significant benefits in
   breaking transparency."  [RFC2616]

The phrase "WOULD PROBABLY" indicates the authors expectation about what a reasonable implementation is likely to do in a given case. There is no requirement for implementations to be reasonable.

This phrase is also a good example of an aspect of English grammar that is often useful in specification writing, namely the passive- aggressive voice, which provides a meaning in between the active and the passive voice.

   For example: "A SMTP client would probably only want to authenticate
   an SMTP server whose server certificate has a domain name that is the
   domain name that the client thought it was connecting to."  [RFC3207]

The phrase "MAY WISH TO" indicates a behavior that might seem appealing to some people, but which is regarded as ridiculous or unnecessary by others. This phrase is frequently used to avoid further delay in approval of a document.

   For example: "Verifiers MAY wish to track testing mode results to
   assist the Signer."  [RFC6376]

The phrase "COULD" provides a way for specification authors to articulate existential possibilities, in order to provide a hint that might be critical to reliable or secure operation, but without a hard requirement. The lack of a requirement allows for vendor product differentiation.

   For example: "An implementation could mitigate this race condition,
   for example, using timers."  [RFC6733]

The phrase "POSSIBLE" describes what some of the working group members thought of as an edge case that will never happen, but in practice allows the protocol to work at the most fundamental level.

   For example: "It is also possible for the server to send a completion
   response for some other command (if multiple commands are in
   progress), or untagged data."  [RFC3501]

The phrase "MIGHT" conveys a requirement in an intentionally stealthy fashion, to facilitate product differentiation (cf. "COULD" above).

   For example: "In the case of audio and different "m" lines for
   different codecs, an implementation might decide to act as a mixer
   with the different incoming RTP sessions, which is the correct
   behavior."  [RFC5888]

Traditionally, security requirements in IETF documents have been expressed with a mixture of requirements words from RFC 2119 [RFC2119] and the phrases used above. The key words in RFC 2119 are principally useful when threats and mitigations are clear and well defined. The key words in this document can be applied when the threat model is ambiguous, and mitigations are unclear or inconvenient.

   [RFC2119]  Bradner, S., "Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate
              Requirement Levels", BCP 14, RFC 2119, March 1997.

   [RFC0493]  Michener, J., Cotton, I., Kelley, K., Liddle, D., and E.
              Meyer, "GRAPHICS PROTOCOL", RFC 493, April 1973.

   [RFC2616]  Fielding, R., Gettys, J., Mogul, J., Frystyk, H.,
              Masinter, L., Leach, P., and T. Berners-Lee, "Hypertext
              Transfer Protocol -- HTTP/1.1", RFC 2616, June 1999.

   [RFC3207]  Hoffman, P., "SMTP Service Extension for Secure SMTP over
              Transport Layer Security", RFC 3207, February 2002.

   [RFC3501]  Crispin, M., "INTERNET MESSAGE ACCESS PROTOCOL - VERSION
              4rev1", RFC 3501, March 2003.

   [RFC5888]  Camarillo, G. and H. Schulzrinne, "The Session Description
              Protocol (SDP) Grouping Framework", RFC 5888, June 2010.

   [RFC5988]  Nottingham, M., "Web Linking", RFC 5988, October 2010.

   [RFC6120]  Saint-Andre, P., "Extensible Messaging and Presence
              Protocol (XMPP): Core", RFC 6120, March 2011.

   [RFC6376]  Crocker, D., Hansen, T., and M. Kucherawy, "DomainKeys
              Identified Mail (DKIM) Signatures", RFC 6376,
              September 2011.

   [RFC6733]  Fajardo, V., Arkko, J., Loughney, J., and G. Zorn,
              "Diameter Base Protocol", RFC 6733, October 2012.

Authors' Addresses

   Richard Barnes
   BBN
   1300 N 17th St
   Arlington, VA  22209
   US

EMail: rlb@ipv.sx

   Stephen Kent
   BBN
   10 Moulton St
   Cambridge, MA  02138
   US

EMail: kent@bbn.com

   Eric Rescorla
   RTFM, Inc.
   2064 Edgewood Drive
   Palo Alto, CA  94303
   US

EMail: ekr@rtfm.com

This document registers the application/sql media type to be used for the Structured Query Language (SQL).

This document is not an Internet Standards Track specification; it is published for informational purposes.

This document is a product of the Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF). It represents the consensus of the IETF community. It has received public review and has been approved for publication by the Internet Engineering Steering Group (IESG). Not all documents approved by the IESG are a candidate for any level of Internet Standard; see Section 2 of RFC 5741.

Information about the current status of this document, any errata, and how to provide feedback on it may be obtained at http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6922.

Copyright (c) 2013 IETF Trust and the persons identified as the document authors. All rights reserved.

This document is subject to BCP 78 and the IETF Trust's Legal Provisions Relating to IETF Documents (http://trustee.ietf.org/license-info) in effect on the date of publication of this document. Please review these documents carefully, as they describe your rights and restrictions with respect to this document. Code Components extracted from this document must include Simplified BSD License text as described in Section 4.e of the Trust Legal Provisions and are provided without warranty as described in the Simplified BSD License.

The Structured Query Language (SQL) has been in use for over 30 years with various types of database technologies. However, there is no current media type registered for SQL. Therefore, this document seeks to formally register the application/sql media type to be used for SQL with IANA.

The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in [RFC2119] when they appear in ALL CAPS. These words may also appear in this document in lowercase as English prose, absent of the normative meanings mentioned above.

This section provides the media type registration application for this media type (see [RFC6838], Section 5.6)

Type name: application

Subtype name: sql

Required parameters: N/A

Optional parameters:

      "charset" -- indicates the character set to be used.  When not
      specified, a default value MUST NOT be assumed without inspection
      of the content.

      Implementors should be aware that SQL may carry character set
      information in-band.  In such cases, the "charset" parameter MUST
      NOT be used in order to avoid conflict.  In cases where no
      character set information is supplied in-band, and the character

      set is known, implementors SHOULD use the "charset" parameter.  If
      no in-band or out-of-band character set information is available,
      implementors MUST NOT specify the "charset" parameter.

Encoding considerations:

      If the "charset" parameter is used, the corresponding 7-bit,
      8-bit, or binary encoding may be used.  If the "charset" parameter
      is not used, binary encoding may be required.

Security considerations:

      Being that SQL is a full-fledged programming language and may
      include embedded source code for other programming languages,
      there is a risk of it being used to transfer malware, viruses, and
      other malicious payloads.  Implementors and users are encouraged
      only to exchange SQL files among trusted parties and utilize all
      available security measures, such as restricted access, virus
      scanners, etc., to minimize risk.

      Implementors should be aware that guessing character sets,
      encodings, and possible conflicts between in-band and out-of-band
      character set information may lead to the similar security issues
      as described above.

      Implementors should also be aware that SQL does not provide or
      guarantee any sort of confidentiality and integrity checking, and
      SQL files can expose account information or private information
      about database structure and contents.  It is therefore important
      for applications to provide confidentiality and protection against
      modification by malicious third parties while in transit.

Interoperability considerations:

      While a single standard exists ([ISO.9075.2011]), vendor
      implementations of the standard vary significantly.  Implementors
      and users should make sure that the exchanged SQL files match to
      the specific database/tool and version that they are using.

Published specification:

      The most recent specification of SQL is available in
      [ISO.9075.2011].

Applications that use this media type:

      Databases and related tools

Fragment identifier considerations: N/A

Additional information:

      Deprecated alias names for this type: N/A

      Magic number(s): N/A

      File extension(s): sql

      Macintosh File Type Code(s): N/A

Person & email address to contact for further information:

      Yakov Shafranovich <ietf@shaftek.org>

Intended usage: COMMON

Restrictions on usage: N/A

Author: IESG

Change controller: IESG

Provisional registration? (standards tree only): N/A

IANA has registered "application/sql" in the standards tree of the "Application Media Types" registry, using the application provided in Section 3 of this document.

See the Security Considerations item in the registration template in Section 3, above.

To LTS, thanks for everything.

The author would also like to thank all of the folks at xml.resource.org for providing many of the tools used for preparing RFCs and Internet-Drafts.

A word of thanks to all IETF members who provided feedback on this document.

   [ISO.9075.2011]  International Organization for Standardization,
                    "ISO/IEC 9075:2011, Information Technology -
                    Database Languages -  Structured Query Language
                    (SQL)", 2011.

   [RFC2119]        Bradner, S., "Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate
                    Requirement Levels", BCP 14, RFC 2119, March 1997.

   [RFC6838]        Freed, N., Klensin, J., and T. Hansen, "Media Type
                    Specifications and Registration Procedures", BCP 13,
                    RFC 6838, January 2013.

Author's Address

   Yakov Shafranovich
   BioFortis, Inc.
   10320 Little Patuxent Parkway, Suite 410
   Columbia, MD  21044
   US

Phone: +1 443 276-2464 EMail: ietf@shaftek.org

This document expands, updates, and establishes an IANA registry for the list of URIs intended for use with XML digital signatures, encryption, canonicalization, and key management. These URIs identify algorithms and types of information. This document obsoletes RFC 4051.

This is an Internet Standards Track document.

This document is a product of the Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF). It represents the consensus of the IETF community. It has received public review and has been approved for publication by the Internet Engineering Steering Group (IESG). Further information on Internet Standards is available in Section 2 of RFC 5741.

Information about the current status of this document, any errata, and how to provide feedback on it may be obtained at http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6931.

Copyright (c) 2013 IETF Trust and the persons identified as the document authors. All rights reserved.

This document is subject to BCP 78 and the IETF Trust's Legal Provisions Relating to IETF Documents (http://trustee.ietf.org/license-info) in effect on the date of publication of this document. Please review these documents carefully, as they describe your rights and restrictions with respect to this document. Code Components extracted from this document must include Simplified BSD License text as described in Section 4.e of the Trust Legal Provisions and are provided without warranty as described in the Simplified BSD License.

XML digital signatures, canonicalization, and encryption have been standardized by the W3C and by the joint IETF/W3C XMLDSIG working group [W3C]. All of these are now W3C Recommendations and some are also RFCs. They are available as follows:

   RFC
   Status            W3C REC      Topic
   -----------       -------      -----

   [RFC3275]         [XMLDSIG10]  XML Digital Signatures
   Draft Standard

   [RFC3076]         [CANON10]    Canonical XML
   Informational

   - - - - - -       [XMLENC10]   XML Encryption 1.0

   [RFC3741]         [XCANON]     Exclusive XML Canonicalization 1.0
   Informational

All of these documents and recommendations use URIs [RFC3986] to identify algorithms and keying information types. The W3C has subsequently produced updated XML Signature 1.1 [XMLDSIG11], Canonical XML 1.1 [CANON11], and XML Encryption 1.1 [XMLENC11] versions, as well as a new XML Signature Properties specification [XMLDSIG-PROP].

All camel-case element names herein, such as DigestValue, are from these documents.

This document is an updated convenient reference list of URIs and corresponding algorithms in which there is expressed interest. Since the previous list [RFC4051] was issued in 2005, significant new cryptographic algorithms of interest to XML security, for some of which the URI is only specified in this document, have been added. This document obsoletes [RFC4051]. All of the URIs appear in the indexes in Section 4. Only the URIs that were added by [RFC4051] or this document have a subsection in Section 2 or 3, with the exception of Minimal Canonicalization (Section 2.4), for example, use of

SHA-256 is defined in [XMLENC11] and hence there is no subsection on that algorithm here, but its URI is included in the indexes in Section 4.

Specification in this document of the URI representing an algorithm does not imply endorsement of the algorithm for any particular purpose. A protocol specification, which this is not, generally gives algorithm and implementation requirements for the protocol. Security considerations for algorithms are constantly evolving, as documented elsewhere. This specification simply provides some URIs and relevant formatting for when those URIs are used.

Note that progressing XML Digital Signature [RFC3275] along the Standards Track required removal of any algorithms from the original version [RFC3075] for which there was not demonstrated interoperability. This required removal of the Minimal Canonicalization algorithm, in which there appears to be continued interest. The URI for Minimal Canonicalization was included in [RFC4051] and is included here.

The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in [RFC2119].

This document is not intended to change the algorithm implementation requirements of any IETF or W3C document. Use of [RFC2119] terminology is intended to be only such as is already stated or implied by other authoritative documents.

The following acronyms are used in this document:

HMAC - Keyed-Hashing MAC [RFC2104]

IETF - Internet Engineering Task Force <www.ietf.org>

MAC - Message Authentication Code

MD - Message Digest

   NIST - United States National Institute of Standards and Technology
          <www.nist.gov>

RC - Rivest Cipher

RSA - Rivest, Shamir, and Adleman

SHA - Secure Hash Algorithm

URI - Uniform Resource Identifier [RFC3986]

W3C - World Wide Web Consortium <www.w3.org>

XML - eXtensible Markup Language

The URI [RFC3986] that was dropped from the XML Digital Signature standard due to the transition from Proposed Standard to Draft Standard [RFC3275] is included in Section 2.4 below with its original

      http://www.w3.org/2000/09/xmldsig#

prefix so as to avoid changing the XMLDSIG standard's namespace.

Additional algorithms in [RFC4051] were given URIs that start with

      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#

while further algorithms added in this document are given URIs that start with

      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#

In addition, for ease of reference, this document includes in the indexes in Section 4 many cryptographic algorithm URIs from several XML security documents using the namespaces with which they are defined in those documents. For example, 2000/09/xmldsig# for some URIs specified in [RFC3275] and 2001/04/xmlenc# for some URIs specified in [XMLENC10].

See also [XMLSECXREF].

These algorithms are usable wherever a DigestMethod element occurs.

   Identifier:
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#md5

The MD5 algorithm [RFC1321] takes no explicit parameters. An example of an MD5 DigestAlgorithm element is:

   <DigestAlgorithm
      Algorithm="http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#md5"/>

An MD5 digest is a 128-bit string. The content of the DigestValue element SHALL be the base64 [RFC2045] encoding of this bit string viewed as a 16-octet stream. See [RFC6151] for MD5 security considerations.

   Identifier:
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#sha224

The SHA-224 algorithm [FIPS180-4] [RFC6234] takes no explicit parameters. An example of a SHA-224 DigestAlgorithm element is:

   <DigestAlgorithm
      Algorithm="http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#sha224" />

A SHA-224 digest is a 224-bit string. The content of the DigestValue element SHALL be the base64 [RFC2045] encoding of this string viewed as a 28-octet stream.

   Identifier:
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#sha384

The SHA-384 algorithm [FIPS180-4] takes no explicit parameters. An example of a SHA-384 DigestAlgorithm element is:

   <DigestAlgorithm
      Algorithm="http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#sha384" />

A SHA-384 digest is a 384-bit string. The content of the DigestValue element SHALL be the base64 [RFC2045] encoding of this string viewed as a 48-octet stream.

   Identifier:
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#whirlpool

The Whirlpool algorithm [10118-3] takes no explicit parameters. A Whirlpool digest is a 512-bit string. The content of the DigestValue element SHALL be the base64 [RFC2045] encoding of this string viewed as a 64-octet stream.

   Identifiers:
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha3-224
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha3-256
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha3-384
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha3-512

NIST has recently completed a hash function competition for an alternative to the SHA family. The Keccak-f[1600] algorithm was selected [Keccak] [SHA-3]. This hash function is commonly referred to as "SHA-3", and this section is a space holder and reservation of URIs for future information on Keccak use in XML security.

A SHA-3 224, 256, 384, and 512 digest is a 224-, 256-, 384-, and 512-bit string, respectively. The content of the DigestValue element SHALL be the base64 [RFC2045] encoding of this string viewed as a 28-, 32-, 48-, and 64-octet stream, respectively.

This section covers SignatureMethod MAC (Message Authentication Code) Algorithms.

Note: Some text in this section is duplicated from [RFC3275] for the convenience of the reader. RFC 3275 is normative in case of conflict.

   Identifier:
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#hmac-md5

The HMAC algorithm [RFC2104] takes the truncation length in bits as a parameter; if the parameter is not specified, then all the bits of the hash are output. An example of an HMAC-MD5 SignatureMethod element is as follows:

   <SignatureMethod
      Algorithm="http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#hmac-md5">
      <HMACOutputLength>112</HMACOutputLength>
   </SignatureMethod>

The output of the HMAC algorithm is ultimately the output (possibly truncated) of the chosen digest algorithm. This value SHALL be base64 [RFC2045] encoded in the same straightforward fashion as the output of the digest algorithms. Example: the SignatureValue element for the HMAC-MD5 digest

      9294727A 3638BB1C 13F48EF8 158BFC9D

from the test vectors in [RFC2104] would be

      kpRyejY4uxwT9I74FYv8nQ==

Schema Definition:

      <simpleType name="HMACOutputLength">
         <restriction base="integer"/>
      </simpleType>

DTD:

      <!ELEMENT HMACOutputLength (#PCDATA) >

The Schema Definition and DTD immediately above are copied from [RFC3275].

See [RFC6151] for HMAC-MD5 security considerations.

   Identifiers:
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#hmac-sha224
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#hmac-sha256
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#hmac-sha384
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#hmac-sha512

SHA-224, SHA-256, SHA-384, and SHA-512 [FIPS180-4] [RFC6234] can also be used in HMAC as described in Section 2.2.1 above for HMAC-MD5.

   Identifier:
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#hmac-ripemd160

RIPEMD-160 [10118-3] can also be used in HMAC as described in Section 2.2.1 above for HMAC-MD5.

These algorithms are distinguished from those in Section 2.2 above in that they use public-key methods. That is to say, the verification key is different from and not feasibly derivable from the signing key.

   Identifier:
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#rsa-md5

This implies the PKCS#1 v1.5 padding algorithm described in [RFC3447]. An example of use is

   <SignatureMethod
      Algorithm="http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#rsa-md5" />

The SignatureValue content for an RSA-MD5 signature is the base64 [RFC2045] encoding of the octet string computed as per [RFC3447], Section 8.2.1, signature generation for the RSASSA-PKCS1-v1_5 signature scheme. As specified in the EMSA-PKCS1-V1_5-ENCODE function in [RFC3447], Section 9.2, the value input to the signature function MUST contain a pre-pended algorithm object identifier for the hash function, but the availability of an ASN.1 parser and recognition of OIDs is not required of a signature verifier. The PKCS#1 v1.5 representation appears as:

      CRYPT (PAD (ASN.1 (OID, DIGEST (data))))

Note that the padded ASN.1 will be of the following form:

      01 | FF* | 00 | prefix | hash

Vertical bar ("|") represents concatenation. "01", "FF", and "00" are fixed octets of the corresponding hexadecimal value, and the asterisk ("*") after "FF" indicates repetition. "hash" is the MD5 digest of the data. "prefix" is the ASN.1 BER MD5 algorithm designator prefix required in PKCS #1 [RFC3447], that is,

      hex 30 20 30 0c 06 08 2a 86 48 86 f7 0d 02 05 05 00 04 10

This prefix is included to make it easier to use standard cryptographic libraries. The FF octet MUST be repeated enough times that the value of the quantity being CRYPTed is exactly one octet shorter than the RSA modulus.

See [RFC6151] for MD5 security considerations.

   Identifier:
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#rsa-sha256

This implies the PKCS#1 v1.5 padding algorithm [RFC3447] as described in Section 2.3.1, but with the ASN.1 BER SHA-256 algorithm designator prefix. An example of use is

   <SignatureMethod
      Algorithm="http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#rsa-sha256"
   />

   Identifier:
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#rsa-sha384

This implies the PKCS#1 v1.5 padding algorithm [RFC3447] as described in Section 2.3.1, but with the ASN.1 BER SHA-384 algorithm designator prefix. An example of use is

   <SignatureMethod
      Algorithm="http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#rsa-sha384" />

Because it takes about the same effort to calculate a SHA-384 message digest as it does a SHA-512 message digest, it is suggested that RSA-SHA512 be used in preference to RSA-SHA384 where possible.

   Identifier:
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#rsa-sha512

This implies the PKCS#1 v1.5 padding algorithm [RFC3447] as described in Section 2.3.1, but with the ASN.1 BER SHA-512 algorithm designator prefix. An example of use is

   <SignatureMethod
      Algorithm="http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#rsa-sha512" />

   Identifier:
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#rsa-ripemd160

This implies the PKCS#1 v1.5 padding algorithm [RFC3447] as described in Section 2.3.1, but with the ASN.1 BER RIPEMD160 algorithm designator prefix. An example of use is

   <SignatureMethod
      Algorithm="http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#rsa-ripemd160"
   />

   Identifiers:
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#ecdsa-sha1
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#ecdsa-sha224
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#ecdsa-sha256
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#ecdsa-sha384
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#ecdsa-sha512
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#ecdsa-ripemd160
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#ecdsa-whirlpool

The Elliptic Curve Digital Signature Algorithm (ECDSA) [FIPS180-4] is the elliptic curve analogue of the Digital Signature Algorithm (DSA) signature method, i.e., the Digital Signature Standard (DSS). It takes no explicit parameters. For detailed specifications of how to use it with SHA hash functions and XML Digital Signature, please see [X9.62] and [RFC4050]. The #ecdsa-ripemd160 and #ecdsa-whirlpool fragments in the new namespace identifies a signature method processed in the same way as specified by the #ecdsa-sha1 fragment of this namespace, with the exception that RIPEMD160 or Whirlpool is used instead of SHA-1.

The output of the ECDSA algorithm consists of a pair of integers usually referred by the pair (r, s). The signature value consists of the base64 encoding of the concatenation of two octet streams that respectively result from the octet-encoding of the values r and s in that order. Conversion from integer to octet stream must be done according to the I2OSP operation defined in the [RFC3447] specification with the l parameter equal to the size of the base point order of the curve in bytes (e.g., 32 for the P-256 curve and 66 for the P-521 curve [FIPS186-3]).

For an introduction to elliptic curve cryptographic algorithms, see [RFC6090] and note the errata (Errata ID 2773-2777).

   Identifiers:
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#esign-sha1
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#esign-sha224
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#esign-sha256
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#esign-sha384
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#esign-sha512

The ESIGN algorithm specified in [IEEEP1363a] is a signature scheme based on the integer factorization problem. It is much faster than previous digital signature schemes, so ESIGN can be implemented on smart cards without special co-processors.

An example of use is

   <SignatureMethod
      Algorithm="http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#esign-sha1"
   />

   Identifier:
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#rsa-whirlpool

   As in the definition of the RSA-SHA1 algorithm in [XMLDSIG11], the
   designator "RSA" means the RSASSA-PKCS1-v1_5 algorithm as defined in
   [RFC3447].  When identified through the #rsa-whirlpool fragment
   identifier, Whirlpool is used as the hash algorithm instead.  Use of
   the ASN.1 BER Whirlpool algorithm designator is implied.  That
   designator is
      hex 30 4e 30 0a 06 06 28 cf 06 03 00 37 05 00 04 40
   as an explicit octet sequence.  This corresponds to OID
   1.0.10118.3.0.55 defined in [10118-3].

An example of use is

   <SignatureMethod
      Algorithm="http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#rsa-whirlpool"
   />

   Identifiers:
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#rsa-pss
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#MGF1

These identifiers imply the PKCS#1 EMSA-PSS encoding algorithm [RFC3447]. The RSASSA-PSS algorithm takes the digest method (hash function), a mask generation function, the salt length in bytes (SaltLength), and the trailer field as explicit parameters.

Algorithm identifiers for hash functions specified in XML encryption [XMLENC11] [XMLDSIG11] and in Section 2.1 are considered to be valid algorithm identifiers for hash functions. According to [RFC3447], the default value for the digest function is SHA-1, but due to the discovered weakness of SHA-1 [RFC6194], it is recommended that SHA-256 or a stronger hash function be used. Notwithstanding [RFC3447], SHA-256 is the default to be used with these SignatureMethod identifiers if no hash function has been specified.

The default salt length for these SignatureMethod identifiers if the SaltLength is not specified SHALL be the number of octets in the hash value of the digest method, as recommended in [RFC4055]. In a parameterized RSASSA-PSS signature the ds:DigestMethod and the SaltLength parameters usually appear. If they do not, the defaults make this equivalent to http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha256-rsa-MGF1 (see Section 2.3.10). The TrailerField defaults to 1 (0xBC) when omitted.

Schema Definition (target namespace http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#):

   <xs:element name="RSAPSSParams" type="pss:RSAPSSParamsType">
       <xs:annotation>
           <xs:documentation>
   Top level element that can be used in xs:any namespace="#other"
   wildcard of ds:SignatureMethod content.
           </xs:documentation>
       </xs:annotation>
   </xs:element>
   <xs:complexType name="RSAPSSParamsType">
       <xs:sequence>
           <xs:element ref="ds:DigestMethod" minOccurs="0"/>
           <xs:element name="MaskGenerationFunction"
              type="pss:MaskGenerationFunctionType" minOccurs="0"/>
           <xs:element name="SaltLength" type="xs:int"
              minOccurs="0"/>
           <xs:element name="TrailerField" type="xs:int"
              minOccurs="0"/>
       </xs:sequence>
   </xs:complexType>
   <xs:complexType name="MaskGenerationFunctionType">
       <xs:sequence>
           <xs:element ref="ds:DigestMethod" minOccurs="0"/>
       </xs:sequence>
       <xs:attribute name="Algorithm" type="xs:anyURI"
          default="http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#MGF1"/>
   </xs:complexType>

[RFC3447] currently specifies only one mask generation function MGF1 based on a hash function. Although [RFC3447] allows for parameterization, the default is to use the same hash function as the digest method function. Only this default approach is supported by this section; therefore, the definition of a mask generation function type is not needed yet. The same applies to the trailer field. There is only one value (0xBC) specified in [RFC3447]. Hence, this default parameter must be used for signature generation. The default salt length is the length of the hash function.

   Identifiers:
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha3-224-rsa-MGF1
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha3-256-rsa-MGF1
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha3-384-rsa-MGF1
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha3-512-rsa-MGF1

      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#md2-rsa-MGF1
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#md5-rsa-MGF1
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha1-rsa-MGF1
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha224-rsa-MGF1
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha256-rsa-MGF1
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha384-rsa-MGF1
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha512-rsa-MGF1
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#ripemd128-rsa-MGF1
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#ripemd160-rsa-MGF1
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#whirlpool-rsa-MGF1

An example of use is

   <SignatureMethod
     Algorithm=
     "http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#SHA3-256-rsa-MGF1"
   />

   Identifier:
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#rsa-sha224

This implies the PKCS#1 v1.5 padding algorithm [RFC3447] as described in Section 2.3.1, but with the ASN.1 BER SHA-224 algorithm designator prefix. An example of use is

   <SignatureMethod
      Algorithm="http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#rsa-sha224" />

Because it takes about the same effort to calculate a SHA-224 message digest as it does a SHA-256 message digest, it is suggested that RSA-SHA256 be used in preference to RSA-SHA224 where possible.

Thus far, two independent interoperable implementations of Minimal Canonicalization have not been announced. Therefore, when XML Digital Signature was advanced along the Standards Track from [RFC3075] to [RFC3275], Minimal Canonicalization was dropped. However, there is still interest. For its definition, see Section 6.5.1 of [RFC3075].

   For reference, its identifier remains:
      http://www.w3.org/2000/09/xmldsig#minimal

Note that all CanonicalizationMethod algorithms can also be used as transform algorithms.

   Identifier:
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#xptr

This transform algorithm takes an [XPointer] as an explicit parameter. An example of use is:

   <Transform
      Algorithm="http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more/xptr">
      <XPointer
         xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more/xptr">
            xpointer(id("foo")) xmlns(bar=http://foobar.example)
            xpointer(//bar:Zab[@Id="foo"])
      </XPointer>
   </Transform>

Schema Definition:

      <element name="XPointer" type="string"/>

DTD:

      <!ELEMENT XPointer (#PCDATA) >

Input to this transform is an octet stream (which is then parsed into XML).

Output from this transform is a node set; the results of the XPointer are processed as defined in the XMLDSIG specification [RFC3275] for a same-document XPointer.

This subsection gives identifiers and information for several EncryptionMethod Algorithms.

   Identifier:
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#arcfour

ARCFOUR is a fast, simple stream encryption algorithm that is compatible with RSA Security's RC4 algorithm [RC4]. An example EncryptionMethod element using ARCFOUR is

   <EncryptionMethod
      Algorithm="http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#arcfour">
      <KeySize>40</KeySize>
   </EncryptionMethod>

Note that Arcfour makes use of the generic KeySize parameter specified and defined in [XMLENC11].

   Identifiers:
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#camellia128-cbc
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#camellia192-cbc
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#camellia256-cbc

Camellia is a block cipher with the same interface as the AES [Camellia] [RFC3713]; it has a 128-bit block size and 128-, 192-, and 256-bit key sizes. In XML encryption, Camellia is used in the same way as the AES: it is used in the Cipher Block Chaining (CBC) mode with a 128-bit initialization vector (IV). The resulting cipher text is prefixed by the IV. If included in XML output, it is then base64 encoded. An example Camellia EncryptionMethod is as follows:

   <EncryptionMethod
      Algorithm=
      "http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#camellia128-cbc"
   />

   Identifiers:
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#kw-camellia128
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#kw-camellia192
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#kw-camellia256

Camellia [Camellia] [RFC3713] key wrap is identical to the AES key wrap algorithm [RFC3394] specified in the XML Encryption standard with "AES" replaced by "Camellia". As with AES key wrap, the check value is 0xA6A6A6A6A6A6A6A6.

The algorithm is the same whatever the size of the Camellia key used in wrapping, called the "key encrypting key" or "KEK". If Camellia is supported, it is particularly suggested that wrapping 128-bit keys with a 128-bit KEK and wrapping 256-bit keys with a 256-bit KEK be supported.

An example of use is:

   <EncryptionMethod
      Algorithm=
      "http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#kw-camellia128"
   />

   Identifier:
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#psec-kem

The PSEC-KEM algorithm, specified in [18033-2], is a key encapsulation mechanism using elliptic curve encryption.

An example of use is:

   <EncryptionMethod
      Algorithm="http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmlenc#psec-kem">
      <ECParameters>
         <Version>version</Version>
         <FieldID>id</FieldID>
         <Curve>curve</Curve>
         <Base>base</Base>
         <Order>order</Order>
         <Cofactor>cofactor</Cofactor>
      </ECParameters>
   </EncryptionMethod>

See [18033-2] for information on the parameters above.

   Identifier:
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#seed128-cbc

SEED [RFC4269] is a 128-bit block size with 128-bit key sizes. In XML Encryption, SEED can be used in the Cipher Block Chaining (CBC) mode with a 128-bit initialization vector (IV). The resulting cipher text is prefixed by the IV. If included in XML output, it is then base64 encoded.

An example SEED EncryptionMethod is as follows:

   <EncryptionMethod
      Algorithm="http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#seed128-cbc" />

   Identifier:
      http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#kw-seed128

Key wrapping with SEED is identical to Section 2.2.1 of [RFC3394] with "AES" replaced by "SEED". The algorithm is specified in [RFC4010]. The implementation of SEED is optional. The default initial value is 0xA6A6A6A6A6A6A6A6.

An example of use is:

   <EncryptionMethod
      Algorithm=
      "http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#kw-seed128"
   />

In Section 3.1 below a new KeyInfo element child is specified, while in Section 3.2 additional KeyInfo Type values for use in RetrievalMethod are specified.

A PKCS #7 [RFC2315] "signedData" can also be used as a bag of certificates and/or certificate revocation lists (CRLs). The PKCS7signedData element is defined to accommodate such structures within KeyInfo. The binary PKCS #7 structure is base64 [RFC2045] encoded. Any signer information present is ignored. The following is an example [RFC3092], eliding the base64 data:

   <foo:PKCS7signedData
      xmlns:foo="http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more">
      ...
   </foo:PKCS7signedData>

The Type attribute of RetrievalMethod is an optional identifier for the type of data to be retrieved. The result of dereferencing a RetrievalMethod reference for all KeyInfo types with an XML structure is an XML element or document with that element as the root. The various "raw" key information types return a binary value. Thus, they require a Type attribute because they are not unambiguously parsable.

   Identifiers:
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#KeyName
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#KeyValue
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#PKCS7signedData
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#rawPGPKeyPacket
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#rawPKCS7signedData
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#rawSPKISexp
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#rawX509CRL
      http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#RetrievalMethod

The following subsections provide an index by URI and by fragment identifier (the portion of the URI after "#") of the algorithm and KeyInfo URIs defined in this document and in the standards (plus the one KeyInfo child element name defined in this document). The "Sec/Doc" column has the section of this document or, if not specified in this document, the document where the item is specified. See also [XMLSECXREF].

The initial "http://www.w3.org/" part of the URI is not included below. The first six entries have a null fragment identifier or no fragment identifier.

   Fragment            URI                                   Sec/Doc
   ---------           ----                                 --------

                       2002/06/xmldsig-filter2                [XPATH]
                       2006/12/xmlc12n11#                   [CANON11]
                       TR/1999/REC-xslt-19991116               [XSLT]
                       TR/1999/REC-xpath-19991116             [XPATH]
                       TR/2001/06/xml-exc-c14n#              [XCANON]
                       TR/2001/REC-xml-c14n-20010315        [CANON10]
                       TR/2001/REC-xmlschema-1-20010502      [Schema]

   aes128-cbc          2001/04/xmlenc#aes128-cbc           [XMLENC11]
   aes128-gcm          2009/xmlenc11#aes128-gcm            [XMLENC11]
   aes192-cbc          2001/04/xmlenc#aes192-cbc           [XMLENC11]
   aes192-gcm          2009/xmlenc11#aes192-gcm            [XMLENC11]
   aes256-cbc          2001/04/xmlenc#aes256-cbc           [XMLENC11]
   aes256-gcm          2009/xmlenc11#aes256-gcm            [XMLENC11]
   arcfour             2001/04/xmldsig-more#arcfour            2.6.1

   base64              2000/09/xmldsig#base64               [RFC3275]

   camellia128-cbc     2001/04/xmldsig-more#camellia128-cbc    2.6.2
   camellia192-cbc     2001/04/xmldsig-more#camellia192-cbc    2.6.2
   camellia256-cbc     2001/04/xmldsig-more#camellia256-cbc    2.6.2
   ConcatKDF           2009/xmlenc11#ConcatKDF             [XMLENC11]

   decrypt#XML         2002/07/decrypt#XML                  [DECRYPT]
   decrypt#Binary      2002/07/decrypt#Binary               [DECRYPT]
   DEREncodedKeyValue  2009/xmldsig11#DEREncodedKeyValue  [XMLDSIG11]
   dh                  2001/04/xmlenc#dh                   [XMLENC11]
   dh-es               2009/xmlenc11#dh-es                 [XMLENC11]
   dsa-sha1            2000/09/xmldsig#dsa-sha1             [RFC3275]
   dsa-sha256          2009/xmldsig11#dsa-sha256          [XMLDSIG11]
   DSAKeyValue         2000/09/xmldsig#DSAKeyValue        [XMLDSIG11]

   ECDH-ES             2009/xmlenc11#ECDH-ES               [XMLENC11]
   ecdsa-ripemd160     2007/05/xmldsig-more#ecdsa-ripemd160    2.3.6
   ecdsa-sha1          2001/04/xmldsig-more#ecdsa-sha1         2.3.6
   ecdsa-sha224        2001/04/xmldsig-more#ecdsa-sha224       2.3.6
   ecdsa-sha256        2001/04/xmldsig-more#ecdsa-sha256       2.3.6
   ecdsa-sha384        2001/04/xmldsig-more#ecdsa-sha384       2.3.6
   ecdsa-sha512        2001/04/xmldsig-more#ecdsa-sha512       2.3.6

   ecdsa-whirlpool     2007/05/xmldsig-more#ecdsa-whirlpool    2.3.5
   ecies-kem           2010/xmlsec-ghc#ecies-kem            [GENERIC]
   ECKeyValue          2009/xmldsig11#ECKeyValue          [XMLDSIG11]
   enveloped-signature 2000/09/xmldsig#enveloped-signature  [RFC3275]
   esign-sha1          2001/04/xmldsig-more#esign-sha1         2.3.7
   esign-sha224        2001/04/xmldsig-more#esign-sha224       2.3.7
   esign-sha256        2001/04/xmldsig-more#esign-sha256       2.3.7
   esign-sha384        2001/04/xmldsig-more#esign-sha384       2.3.7
   esign-sha512        2001/04/xmldsig-more#esign-sha512       2.3.7

   generic-hybrid      2010/xmlsec-ghc#generic-hybrid       [GENERIC]

   hmac-md5            2001/04/xmldsig-more#hmac-md5           2.2.1
   hmac-ripemd160      2001/04/xmldsig-more#hmac-ripemd160     2.2.3
   hmac-sha1           2000/09/xmldsig#hmac-sha1            [RFC3275]
   hmac-sha224         2001/04/xmldsig-more#hmac-sha224        2.2.2
   hmac-sha256         2001/04/xmldsig-more#hmac-sha256        2.2.2
   hmac-sha384         2001/04/xmldsig-more#hmac-sha384        2.2.2
   hmac-sha512         2001/04/xmldsig-more#hmac-sha512        2.2.2

   KeyName             2001/04/xmldsig-more#KeyName            3.2
   KeyValue            2001/04/xmldsig-more#KeyValue           3.2
   kw-aes128           2001/04/xmlenc#kw-aes128            [XMLENC11]
   kw-aes128-pad       2009/xmlenc11#kw-aes-128-pad        [XMLENC11]
   kw-aes192           2001/04/xmlenc#kw-aes192            [XMLENC11]
   kw-aes192-pad       2009/xmlenc11#kw-aes-192-pad        [XMLENC11]
   kw-aes256           2001/04/xmlenc#kw-aes256            [XMLENC11]
   kw-aes256-pad       2009/xmlenc11#kw-aes-256-pad        [XMLENC11]
   kw-camellia128      2001/04/xmldsig-more#kw-camellia128     2.6.3
   kw-camellia192      2001/04/xmldsig-more#kw-camellia192     2.6.3
   kw-camellia256      2001/04/xmldsig-more#kw-camellia256     2.6.3
   kw-seed128          2007/05/xmldsig-more#kw-seed128         2.6.6

   md2-rsa-MGF1        2007/05/xmldsig-more#md2-rsa-MGF1       2.3.10
   md5                 2001/04/xmldsig-more#md5                2.1.1
   md5-rsa-MGF1        2007/05/xmldsig-more#md5-rsa-MGF1       2.3.10
   MGF1                2007/05/xmldsig-more#MGF1               2.3.9
   mgf1sha1            2009/xmlenc11#mgf1sha1              [XMLENC11]
   mgf1sha224          2009/xmlenc11#mgf1sha224            [XMLENC11]
   mgf1sha256          2009/xmlenc11#mgf1sha256            [XMLENC11]
   mgf1sha384          2009/xmlenc11#mgf1sha384            [XMLENC11]
   mgf1sha512          2009/xmlenc11#mgf1sha512            [XMLENC11]
   MgmtData            2000/09/xmldsig#MgmtData           [XMLDSIG11]
   minimal             2000/09/xmldsig#minimal                 2.4

   pbkdf2              2009/xmlenc11#pbkdf2                [XMLENC11]
   PGPData             2000/09/xmldsig#PGPData            [XMLDSIG11]
   PKCS7signedData     2001/04/xmldsig-more#PKCS7signedData    3.1

   PKCS7signedData     2001/04/xmldsig-more#PKCS7signedData    3.2
   psec-kem            2001/04/xmldsig-more#psec-kem           2.6.4

   rawPGPKeyPacket     2001/04/xmldsig-more#rawPGPKeyPacket    3.2
   rawPKCS7signedData  2001/04/xmldsig-more#rawPKCS7signedData 3.2
   rawSPKISexp         2001/04/xmldsig-more#rawSPKISexp        3.2
   rawX509Certificate  2000/09/xmldsig#rawX509Certificate   [RFC3275]
   rawX509CRL          2001/04/xmldsig-more#rawX509CRL         3.2
   RetrievalMethod     2001/04/xmldsig-more#RetrievalMethod    3.2
   ripemd128-rsa-MGF1  2007/05/xmldsig-more#ripemd128-rsa-MGF1 2.3.10
   ripemd160           2001/04/xmlenc#ripemd160            [XMLENC11]
   ripemd160-rsa-MGF1  2007/05/xmldsig-more#ripemd160-rsa-MGF1 2.3.10
   rsa-1_5             2001/04/xmlenc#rsa-1_5              [XMLENC11]
   rsa-md5             2001/04/xmldsig-more#rsa-md5            2.3.1
   rsa-oaep            2009/xmlenc11#rsa-oaep              [XMLENC11]
   rsa-oaep-mgf1p      2001/04/xmlenc#rsa-oaep-mgf1p       [XMLENC11]
   rsa-pss             2007/05/xmldsig-more#rsa-pss            2.3.9
   rsa-ripemd160       2001/04/xmldsig-more#rsa-ripemd160      2.3.5
   rsa-sha1            2000/09/xmldsig#rsa-sha1             [RFC3275]
   rsa-sha224          2007/05/xmldsig-more#rsa-sha224         2.3.11
   rsa-sha256          2001/04/xmldsig-more#rsa-sha256         2.3.2
   rsa-sha384          2001/04/xmldsig-more#rsa-sha384         2.3.3
   rsa-sha512          2001/04/xmldsig-more#rsa-sha512         2.3.4
   rsa-whirlpool       2007/05/xmldsig-more#rsa-whirlpool      2.3.5
   rsaes-kem           2010/xmlsec-ghc#rsaes-kem            [GENERIC]
   RSAKeyValue         2000/09/xmldsig#RSAKeyValue        [XMLDSIG11]

   seed128-cbc         2007/05/xmldsig-more#seed128-cbc        2.6.5
   sha1                2000/09/xmldsig#sha1                 [RFC3275]
   sha1-rsa-MGF1       2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha1-rsa-MGF1      2.3.10
   sha224              2001/04/xmldsig-more#sha224             2.1.2
   sha224-rsa-MGF1     2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha224-rsa-MGF1    2.3.10
   sha256              2001/04/xmlenc#sha256               [XMLENC11]
   sha256-rsa-MGF1     2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha256-rsa-MGF1    2.3.10
   sha3-224            2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha3-224           2.1.5
   sha3-224-rsa-MGF1   2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha3-224-rsa-MGF1  2.3.10
   sha3-256            2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha3-256           2.1.5
   sha3-256-rsa-MGF1   2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha3-256-rsa-MGF1  2.3.10
   sha3-384            2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha3-384           2.1.5
   sha3-384-rsa-MGF1   2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha3-384-rsa-MGF1  2.3.10
   sha3-512            2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha3-512           2.1.5
   sha3-512-rsa-MGF1   2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha3-512-rsa-MGF1  2.3.10
   sha384              2001/04/xmldsig-more#sha384             2.1.3
   sha384-rsa-MGF1     2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha384-rsa-MGF1    2.3.10
   sha512              2001/04/xmlenc#sha512               [XMLENC11]
   sha512-rsa-MGF1     2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha512-rsa-MGF1    2.3.10
   SPKIData            2000/09/xmldsig#SPKIData           [XMLDSIG11]

   tripledes-cbc       2001/04/xmlenc#tripledes-cbc        [XMLENC11]

   whirlpool           2007/05/xmldsig-more#whirlpool          2.1.4
   whirlpool-rsa-MGF1  2007/05/xmldsig-more#whirlpool-rsa-MGF1 2.3.10
   WithComments        2006/12/xmlc14n11#WithComments       [CANON11]
   WithComments        TR/2001/06/xml-exc-c14n#WithComments  [XCANON]
   WithComments        TR/2001/REC-xml-c14n-20010315#WithComments
                                                            [CANON10]

   X509Data            2000/09/xmldsig#X509Data           [XMLDSIG11]
   xptr                2001/04/xmldsig-more#xptr               2.5.1

The initial "http://www.w3.org/" part of the URI is not included above.

The initial "http://www.w3.org/" part of the URI is not included below.

   URI                                 Sec/Doc   Type
   ----                                --------  -----

   2000/09/xmldsig#base64              [RFC3275]  Transform
   2000/09/xmldsig#DSAKeyValue         [RFC3275]  Retrieval type
   2000/09/xmldsig#dsa-sha1            [RFC3275]  SignatureMethod
   2000/09/xmldsig#enveloped-signature [RFC3275]  Transform
   2000/09/xmldsig#hmac-sha1           [RFC3275]  SignatureMethod
   2000/09/xmldsig#MgmtData            [RFC3275]  Retrieval type
   2000/09/xmldsig#minimal                2.4     Canonicalization
   2000/09/xmldsig#PGPData             [RFC3275]  Retrieval type
   2000/09/xmldsig#rawX509Certificate  [RFC3275]  Retrieval type
   2000/09/xmldsig#rsa-sha1            [RFC3275]  SignatureMethod
   2000/09/xmldsig#RSAKeyValue         [RFC3275]  Retrieval type
   2000/09/xmldsig#sha1                [RFC3275]  DigestAlgorithm
   2000/09/xmldsig#SPKIData            [RFC3275]  Retrieval type
   2000/09/xmldsig#X509Data            [RFC3275]  Retrieval type

   2001/04/xmldsig-more#arcfour           2.6.1   EncryptionMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#camellia128-cbc   2.6.2   EncryptionMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#camellia192-cbc   2.6.2   EncryptionMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#camellia256-cbc   2.6.2   EncryptionMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#ecdsa-sha1        2.3.6   SignatureMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#ecdsa-sha224      2.3.6   SignatureMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#ecdsa-sha256      2.3.6   SignatureMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#ecdsa-sha384      2.3.6   SignatureMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#ecdsa-sha512      2.3.6   SignatureMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#esign-sha1        2.3.7   SignatureMethod

   2001/04/xmldsig-more#esign-sha224      2.3.7   SignatureMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#esign-sha256      2.3.7   SignatureMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#esign-sha384      2.3.7   SignatureMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#esign-sha512      2.3.7   SignatureMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#hmac-md5          2.2.1   SignatureMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#hmac-ripemd160    2.2.3   SignatureMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#hmac-sha224       2.2.2   SignatureMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#hmac-sha256       2.2.2   SignatureMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#hmac-sha384       2.2.2   SignatureMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#hmac-sha512       2.2.2   SignatureMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#KeyName           3.2     Retrieval type
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#KeyValue          3.2     Retrieval type
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#kw-camellia128    2.6.3   EncryptionMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#kw-camellia192    2.6.3   EncryptionMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#kw-camellia256    2.6.3   EncryptionMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#md5               2.1.1   DigestAlgorithm
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#PKCS7signedData   3.2     Retrieval type
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#psec-kem          2.6.4   EncryptionMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#rawPGPKeyPacket   3.2     Retrieval type
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#rawPKCS7signedData 3.2    Retrieval type
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#rawSPKISexp       3.2     Retrieval type
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#rawX509CRL        3.2     Retrieval type
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#RetrievalMethod   3.2     Retrieval type
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#rsa-md5           2.3.1   SignatureMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#rsa-sha256        2.3.2   SignatureMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#rsa-sha384        2.3.3   SignatureMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#rsa-sha512        2.3.4   SignatureMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#rsa-ripemd160     2.3.5   SignatureMethod
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#sha224            2.1.2   DigestAlgorithm
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#sha384            2.1.3   DigestAlgorithm
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#xptr              2.5.1   Transform
   2001/04/xmldsig-more#PKCS7signedData   3.1     KeyInfo child

   2001/04/xmlenc#aes128-cbc          [XMLENC11]  EncryptionMethod
   2001/04/xmlenc#aes192-cbc          [XMLENC11]  EncryptionMethod
   2001/04/xmlenc#aes256-cbc          [XMLENC11]  EncryptionMethod
   2001/04/xmlenc#dh                  [XMLENC11]  AgreementMethod
   2001/04/xmlenc#kw-aes128           [XMLENC11]  EncryptionMethod
   2001/04/xmlenc#kw-aes192           [XMLENC11]  EncryptionMethod
   2001/04/xmlenc#kw-aes256           [XMLENC11]  EncryptionMethod
   2001/04/xmlenc#ripemd160           [XMLENC11]  DigestAlgorithm
   2001/04/xmlenc#rsa-1_5             [XMLENC11]  EncryptionMethod
   2001/04/xmlenc#rsa-oaep-mgf1p      [XMLENC11]  EncryptionMethod
   2001/04/xmlenc#sha256              [XMLENC11]  DigestAlgorithm
   2001/04/xmlenc#sha512              [XMLENC11]  DigestAlgorithm
   2001/04/xmlenc#tripledes-cbc       [XMLENC11]  EncryptionMethod

   2002/06/xmldsig-filter2               [XPATH]  Transform

   2002/07/decrypt#XML                 [DECRYPT]  Transform
   2002/07/decrypt#Binary              [DECRYPT]  Transform

   2006/12/xmlc12n11#                  [CANON11]  Canonicalization
   2006/12/xmlc14n11#WithComments      [CANON11]  Canonicalization

   2007/05/xmldsig-more#ecdsa-ripemd160   2.3.6   SignatureMethod
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#ecdsa-whirlpool   2.3.5   SignatureMethod
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#kw-seed128        2.6.6   EncryptionMethod
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#md2-rsa-MGF1      2.3.10  SignatureMethod
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#md5-rsa-MGF1      2.3.10  SignatureMethod
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#MGF1              2.3.9   SignatureMethod
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#ripemd128-rsa-MGF1 2.3.10 SignatureMethod
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#ripemd160-rsa-MGF1 2.3.10 SignatureMethod
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#rsa-pss           2.3.9   SignatureMethod
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#rsa-sha224        2.3.11  SignatureMethod
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#rsa-whirlpool     2.3.5   SignatureMethod
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#seed128-cbc       2.6.5   EncryptionMethod
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha1-rsa-MGF1     2.3.10  SignatureMethod
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha224-rsa-MGF1   2.3.10  SignatureMethod
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha256-rsa-MGF1   2.3.10  SignatureMethod
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha3-224          2.1.5   DigestAlgorithm
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha3-224-rsa-MGF1 2.3.10  SignatureMethod
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha3-256          2.1.5   DigestAlgorithm
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha3-256-rsa-MGF1 2.3.10  SignatureMethod
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha3-384          2.1.5   DigestAlgorithm
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha3-384-rsa-MGF1 2.3.10  SignatureMethod
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha3-512          2.1.5   DigestAlgorithm
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha3-512-rsa-MGF1 2.3.10  SignatureMethod
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha384-rsa-MGF1   2.3.10  SignatureMethod
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#sha512-rsa-MGF1   2.3.10  SignatureMethod
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#whirlpool         2.1.4   DigestAlgorithm
   2007/05/xmldsig-more#whirlpool-rsa-MGF1 2.3.10 SignatureMethod
   2009/xmlenc11#kw-aes-128-pad       [XMLENC11]  EncryptionMethod
   2009/xmlenc11#kw-aes-192-pad       [XMLENC11]  EncryptionMethod
   2009/xmlenc11#kw-aes-256-pad       [XMLENC11]  EncryptionMethod

   2009/xmldsig11#dsa-sha256         [XMLDSIG11]  SignatureMethod
   2009/xmldsig11#ECKeyValue         [XMLDSIG11]  Retrieval type
   2009/xmldsig11#DEREncodedKeyValue [XMLDSIG11]  Retrieval type

   2009/xmlenc11#aes128-gcm           [XMLENC11]  EncryptionMethod
   2009/xmlenc11#aes192-gcm           [XMLENC11]  EncryptionMethod
   2009/xmlenc11#aes256-gcm           [XMLENC11]  EncryptionMethod
   2009/xmlenc11#ConcatKDF            [XMLENC11]  EncryptionMethod
   2009/xmlenc11#mgf1sha1             [XMLENC11]  SignatureMethod
   2009/xmlenc11#mgf1sha224           [XMLENC11]  SignatureMethod
   2009/xmlenc11#mgf1sha256           [XMLENC11]  SignatureMethod

   2009/xmlenc11#mgf1sha384           [XMLENC11]  SignatureMethod
   2009/xmlenc11#mgf1sha512           [XMLENC11]  SignatureMethod
   2009/xmlenc11#pbkdf2               [XMLENC11]  EncryptionMethod
   2009/xmlenc11#rsa-oaep             [XMLENC11]  EncryptionMethod
   2009/xmlenc11#ECDH-ES              [XMLENC11]  EncryptionMethod
   2009/xmlenc11#dh-es                [XMLENC11]  EncryptionMethod

   2010/xmlsec-ghc#generic-hybrid      [GENERIC]  Generic Hybrid
   2010/xmlsec-ghc#rsaes-kem           [GENERIC]  Generic Hybrid
   2010/xmlsec-ghc#ecies-kem           [GENERIC]  Generic Hybrid

   TR/1999/REC-xpath-19991116            [XPATH]  Transform
   TR/1999/REC-xslt-19991116              [XSLT]  Transform
   TR/2001/06/xml-exc-c14n#             [XCANON]  Canonicalization
   TR/2001/06/xml-exc-c14n#WithComments [XCANON]  Canonicalization
   TR/2001/REC-xml-c14n-20010315       [CANON10]  Canonicalization
   TR/2001/REC-xml-c14n-20010315#WithComments
                                       [CANON10]  Canonicalization
   TR/2001/REC-xmlschema-1-20010502     [Schema]  Transform

The initial "http://www.w3.org/" part of the URI is not included above.

W3C and IANA allocation considerations are given below.

As it is easy for people to construct their own unique URIs [RFC3986] and, if appropriate, to obtain a URI from the W3C, it is not intended that any additional "http://www.w3.org/2007/05/xmldsig-more#" URIs be created beyond those enumerated in this RFC. (W3C Namespace stability rules prohibit the creation of new URIs under "http://www.w3.org/2000/09/xmldsig#" and URIs under "http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#" were frozen with the publication of [RFC4051].)

An "xmldsig-more" URI does not imply any official W3C or IETF status for these algorithms or identifiers nor does it imply that they are only useful in digital signatures. Currently, dereferencing such URIs may or may not produce a temporary placeholder document. Permission to use these URI prefixes has been given by the W3C.

IANA has established a registry entitled "XML Security URIs". The initial contents correspond to Section 4.2 of this document with each section number in the "Sec/Doc" column augmented with a reference to this RFC (for example, "2.6.4" means "[RFC6931], Section 2.6.4").

New entries, including new Types, will be added based on Expert Review [RFC5226]. Criterion for inclusion are (1) documentation sufficient for interoperability of the algorithm or data type and the XML syntax for its representation and use and (2) sufficient importance as normally indicated by inclusion in (2a) an approved W3C Note, Proposed Recommendation, or Recommendation or (2b) an approved IETF Standards Track document. Typically, the registry will reference a W3C or IETF document specifying such XML syntax; that document will either contain a more abstract description of the algorithm or data type or reference another document with a more abstract description.

This RFC is concerned with documenting the URIs that designate algorithms and some data types used in connection with XML security. The security considerations vary widely with the particular algorithms, and the general security considerations for XML security are outside of the scope of this document but appear in [XMLDSIG11], [XMLENC11], [CANON10], [CANON11], and [GENERIC].

[RFC6151] should be consulted before considering the use of MD5 as a DigestMethod or RSA-MD5 as a SignatureMethod.

See [RFC6194] for SHA-1 security considerations and [RFC6151] for MD5 security considerations.

Additional security considerations are given in connection with the description of some algorithms in the body of this document.

Implementers should be aware that cryptographic algorithms become weaker with time. As new cryptoanalysis techniques are developed and computing performance improves, the work factor to break a particular cryptographic algorithm will reduce. Therefore, cryptographic implementations should be modular, allowing new algorithms to be readily inserted. That is, implementers should be prepared for the set of mandatory-to-implement algorithms to change over time.

The contributions to this document by the following people, listed in alphabetic order, are gratefully acknowledged: Benoit Claise, Adrian Farrel, Stephen Farrell, Ernst Giessmann, Frederick Hirsch, Bjoern Hoehrmann, Russ Housley, Satoru Kanno, Charlie Kaufman, Konrad Lanz, HwanJin Lee, Barry Leiba, Peter Lipp, Subramanian Moonesamy, Thomas Roessler, Hanseong Ryu, Peter Saint-Andre, and Sean Turner.

The following contributors to [RFC4051], on which this document is based, are gratefully acknowledged: Glenn Adams, Merlin Hughs, Gregor Karlinger, Brian LaMachia, Shiho Moriai, Joseph Reagle, Russ Housley, and Joel Halpern.

Appendix A. Changes from RFC 4051

The following changes have been made in RFC 4051 to produce this document.

   1.  Updated and added numerous RFC, W3C, and Internet-Draft
       references.

   2.  Added #ecdsa-ripemd160, #whirlpool, #ecdsa-whirlpool,
       #rsa-whirlpool, #seed128-cbc, and #kw-seed128.

3. Incorporated RFC 4051 errata [Errata191].

4. Added URI and fragment index sections.

5. For MD5 and SHA-1, added references to [RFC6151] and [RFC6194].

   5.  Added SHA-3 / Keccak placeholder section including #sha3-224,
       #sha3-256, #sha3-384, and #sha3-512.

   6.  Added RSASSA-PSS sections including #sha3-224-MGF1,
       #sha3-256-MGF1, #sha3-384-MGF1, #sha3-512-MGF1, #md2-rsa-MGF1,
       #md5-rsa-MGF1, #sha1-rsa-MGF1, #sha224-rsa-MGF1,
       #sha256-rsa-MGF1, #sha384-rsa-MGF1, #sha512-rsa-MGF1,
       #ripemd128-rsa-MGF1, #ripemd160-rsa-MGF1, and
       #whirlpool-rsa-MGF1.

   7.  Added new URIs from Canonical XML 1.1 and XML Encryption 1.1
       including: #aes128-gcm, #aes192-gcm, #aes256-gc, #ConcatKDF,
       #pbkdf, #rsa-oaep, #ECDH-ES, and #dh-es.

8. Added acronym subsection.

   9.  Added numerous URIs that are specified in W3C XML Security
       documents to the Indexes.  These do not have sections in the body
       of this document -- for example, those for dsa-sha256, mgf1sha*,
       decrypt#XML, and xmldsig-filter2.

10. Requested establishment of an IANA registry.

11. Made various editorial changes.

Normative References

   [10118-3]     ISO, "Information technology -- Security techniques --
                 Hash-functions -- Part 3: Dedicated hash-functions",
                 ISO/IEC 10118-3:2004, 2004.

   [18033-2]     ISO, "Information technology -- Security techniques --
                 Encryption algorithms -- Part 3: Asymmetric ciphers",
                 ISO/IEC 18033-2:2010, 2010.

   [Camellia]    Aoki, K., Ichikawa, T., Matsui, M., Moriai, S.,
                 Nakajima, J., and T. Tokita, "Camellia: A 128-bit Block
                 Cipher Suitable for Multiple Platforms - Design and
                 Analysis", in Selected Areas in Cryptography, 7th
                 Annual International Workshop, SAC 2000, August 2000,
                 Proceedings, Lecture Notes in Computer Science 2012,
                 pp. 39-56, Springer-Verlag, 2001.

   [FIPS180-4]   US National Institute of Science and Technology,
                 "Secure Hash Standard (SHS)", FIPS 180-4, March 2012,
                 <http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/fips/fips180-4/
                 fips-180-4.pdf>.

   [FIPS186-3]   US National Institute of Science and Technology,
                 "Digital Signature Standard (DSS)", FIPS 186-3, June
                 2009, <http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/fips/
                 fips186-3/fips_186-3.pdf>.

   [IEEEP1363a]  IEEE, "Standard Specifications for Public Key
                 Cryptography- Amendment 1: Additional Techniques", IEEE
                 1363a-2004, 2004.

   [RC4]         Schneier, B., "Applied Cryptography: Protocols,
                 Algorithms, and Source Code in C", Second Edition, John
                 Wiley and Sons, New York, NY, 1996.

   [RFC1321]     Rivest, R., "The MD5 Message-Digest Algorithm", RFC
                 1321, April 1992.

   [RFC2045]     Freed, N. and N. Borenstein, "Multipurpose Internet
                 Mail Extensions (MIME) Part One: Format of Internet
                 Message Bodies", RFC 2045, November 1996.

   [RFC2104]     Krawczyk, H., Bellare, M., and R. Canetti, "HMAC:
                 Keyed-Hashing for Message Authentication", RFC 2104,
                 February 1997.

   [RFC2119]     Bradner, S., "Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate
                 Requirement Levels", BCP 14, RFC 2119, March 1997.

   [RFC2315]     Kaliski, B., "PKCS #7: Cryptographic Message Syntax
                 Version 1.5", RFC 2315, March 1998.

   [RFC3275]     Eastlake 3rd, D., Reagle, J., and D. Solo, "(Extensible
                 Markup Language) XML-Signature Syntax and Processing",
                 RFC 3275, March 2002.

   [RFC3394]     Schaad, J. and R. Housley, "Advanced Encryption
                 Standard (AES) Key Wrap Algorithm", RFC 3394, September
                 2002.

   [RFC3447]     Jonsson, J. and B. Kaliski, "Public-Key Cryptography
                 Standards (PKCS) #1: RSA Cryptography Specifications
                 Version 2.1", RFC 3447, February 2003.

   [RFC3713]     Matsui, M., Nakajima, J., and S. Moriai, "A Description
                 of the Camellia Encryption Algorithm", RFC 3713, April
                 2004.

   [RFC3986]     Berners-Lee, T., Fielding, R., and L. Masinter,
                 "Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic Syntax",
                 STD 66, RFC 3986, January 2005.

   [RFC4050]     Blake-Wilson, S., Karlinger, G., Kobayashi, T., and Y.
                 Wang, "Using the Elliptic Curve Signature Algorithm
                 (ECDSA) for XML Digital Signatures", RFC 4050, April
                 2005.

   [RFC4055]     Schaad, J., Kaliski, B., and R. Housley, "Additional
                 Algorithms and Identifiers for RSA Cryptography for use
                 in the Internet X.509 Public Key Infrastructure
                 Certificate and Certificate Revocation List (CRL)
                 Profile", RFC 4055, June 2005.

   [RFC4269]     Lee, H., Lee, S., Yoon, J., Cheon, D., and J. Lee, "The
                 SEED Encryption Algorithm", RFC 4269, December 2005.

   [RFC5226]     Narten, T. and H. Alvestrand, "Guidelines for Writing
                 an IANA Considerations Section in RFCs", BCP 26, RFC
                 5226, May 2008.

   [RFC6234]     Eastlake 3rd, D. and T. Hansen, "US Secure Hash
                 Algorithms (SHA and SHA-based HMAC and HKDF)", RFC
                 6234, May 2011.

   [X9.62]       American National Standards Institute, Accredited
                 Standards Committee X9, "Public Key Cryptography for
                 the Financial Services Industry: The Elliptic Curve
                 Digital Signature Algorithm (ECDSA)", ANSI X9.62:2005,
                 2005.

   [XMLENC10]    Reagle, J. and D. Eastlake, "XML Encryption Syntax and
                 Processing", W3C Recommendation, 10 December 2002,
                 <http://www.w3.org/TR/2002/REC-xmlenc-core-20021210/>.

   [XMLENC11]    Eastlake, D., Reagle, J., Hirsch, F., and T. Roessler,
                 "XML Encryption Syntax and Processing Version 1.1", W3C
                 Proposed Recommendation, 24 January 2013,
                 <http://www.w3.org/TR/2013/PR-xmlenc-core1-20130124/>.

   [XPointer]    Grosso, P., Maler, E., Marsh, J., and N. Walsh,
                 "XPointer Framework", W3C Recommendation, 25 March
                 2003, <http://www.w3.org/TR/2003/
                 REC-xptr-framework-20030325/>.

Informative References

   [CANON10]     Boyer, J., "Canonical XML Version 1.0", W3C
                 Recommendation, 15 March 2001,
                 <http://www.w3.org/TR/2001/REC-xml-c14n-20010315>.

   [CANON11]     Boyer, J., and G. Marcy, "Canonical XML Version 1.1",
                 W3C Recommendation, 2 May 2008,
                 <http://www.w3.org/TR/2008/REC-xml-c14n11-20080502/>.

   [DECRYPT]     Hughes, M., Imamura, T., and H. Maruyama, "Decryption
                 Transform for XML Signature", W3C Recommendation, 10
                 December 2002, <http://www.w3.org/TR/2002/
                 REC-xmlenc-decrypt-20021210>.

   [Errata191]   RFC Errata, Errata ID 191, RFC 4051,
                 <http://www.rfc-editor.org>.

   [GENERIC]     Nystrom, M. and F. Hirsch, "XML Security Generic Hybrid
                 Ciphers", W3C Working Group Note, 24 January 2013,
                 <http://www.w3.org/TR/2013/
                 NOTE-xmlsec-generic-hybrid-20130124/>.

   [Keccak]      Bertoni, G., Daeman, J., Peeters, M., and G. Van
                 Assche, "The KECCAK sponge function family", January
                 2013, <http://keccak.noekeon.org>.

   [RFC3075]     Eastlake 3rd, D., Reagle, J., and D. Solo, "XML-
                 Signature Syntax and Processing", RFC 3075, March 2001.

   [RFC3076]     Boyer, J., "Canonical XML Version 1.0", RFC 3076, March
                 2001.

   [RFC3092]     Eastlake 3rd, D., Manros, C., and E. Raymond,
                 "Etymology of "Foo"", RFC 3092, 1 April 2001.

   [RFC3741]     Boyer, J., Eastlake 3rd, D., and J. Reagle, "Exclusive
                 XML Canonicalization, Version 1.0", RFC 3741, March
                 2004.

   [RFC4010]     Park, J., Lee, S., Kim, J., and J. Lee, "Use of the
                 SEED Encryption Algorithm in Cryptographic Message
                 Syntax (CMS)", RFC 4010, February 2005.

   [RFC4051]     Eastlake 3rd, D., "Additional XML Security Uniform
                 Resource Identifiers (URIs)", RFC 4051, April 2005.

   [RFC6090]     McGrew, D., Igoe, K., and M. Salter, "Fundamental
                 Elliptic Curve Cryptography Algorithms", RFC 6090,
                 February 2011.

   [RFC6151]     Turner, S. and L. Chen, "Updated Security
                 Considerations for the MD5 Message-Digest and the HMAC-
                 MD5 Algorithms", RFC 6151, March 2011.

   [RFC6194]     Polk, T., Chen, L., Turner, S., and P. Hoffman,
                 "Security Considerations for the SHA-0 and SHA-1
                 Message-Digest Algorithms", RFC 6194, March 2011.

   [Schema]      Thompson, H., Beech, D., Maloney, M., and N.
                 Mendelsohn, "XML Schema Part 1: Structures Second
                 Edition", W3C Recommendation, 28 October 2004,
                 <http://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-xmlschema-1-20041028/>.

                 Biron, P. and A. Malhotra, "XML Schema Part 2:
                 Datatypes Second Edition", W3C Recommendation, 28
                 October 2004,
                 <http://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-xmlschema-2-20041028/>.

   [SHA-3]       US National Institute of Science and Technology, "SHA-3
                 WINNER", February 2013, <http://csrc.nist.gov/
                 groups/ST/hash/sha-3/winner_sha-3.html>.

   [W3C]         World Wide Web Consortium, <http://www.w3.org>.

   [XCANON]      Boyer, J., Eastlake, D., and J. Reagle, "Exclusive XML
                 Canonicalization Version 1.0", W3C Recommendation, 18
                 July 2002,
                 <http://www.w3.org/TR/2002/REC-xml-exc-c14n-20020718/>.

   [XMLDSIG10]   Eastlake, D., Reagle, J., Solo, D., Hirsch, F., and T.
                 Roessler, "XML Signature Syntax and Processing (Second
                 Edition)", W3C Recommendation, 10 June 2008,
                 <http://www.w3.org/TR/2008/REC-xmldsig-core-20080610/>.

   [XMLDSIG11]   Eastlake, D., Reagle, J., Solo, D., Hirsch, F.,
                 Nystrom, M., Roessler, T., and K. Yiu, "XML Signature
                 Syntax and Processing Version 1.1", W3C Proposed
                 Recommendation, 24 January 2013,
                 <http://www.w3.org/TR/2013/PR-xmldsig-core1-20130124/>.

   [XMLDSIG-PROP]
                 Hirsch, F., "XML Signature Properties", W3C Proposed
                 Recommendation, 24 January 2013, <http://www.w3.org/TR/
                 2013/PR-xmldsig-properties-20130124/>.

   [XMLSECXREF]  Hirsch, F., Roessler, T., and K. Yiu, "XML Security
                 Algorithm Cross-Reference", W3C Working Group Note, 24
                 January 2013, <http://www.w3.org/TR/2013/
                 NOTE-xmlsec-algorithms-20130124/>.

   [XPATH]       Boyer, J., Hughes, M., and J. Reagle, "XML-Signature
                 XPath Filter 2.0", W3C Recommendation, 8 November 2002,
                 <http://www.w3.org/TR/2002/
                 REC-xmldsig-filter2-20021108/>.

                 Berglund, A., Boag, S., Chamberlin, D., Fernandez, M.,
                 Kay, M., Robie, J., and J. Simeon, "XML Path Language
                 (XPath) 2.0 (Second Edition)", W3C Recommendation, 14
                 December 2010,
                 <http://www.w3.org/TR/2010/REC-xpath20-20101214/>.

   [XSLT]        Saxonica, M., "XSL Transformations (XSLT) Version 2.0",
                 W3C Recommendation, 23 January 2007,
                 <http://www.w3.org/TR/2007/REC-xslt20-20070123/>.

Author's Address

   Donald E. Eastlake, 3rd
   Huawei Technologies
   155 Beaver Street
   Milford, MA  01757
   USA

Phone: +1-508-333-2270 EMail: d3e3e3@gmail.com